<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The remedie of schisme. Or, a mean to settle the divisions of the times. Set forth in a seasonable sermon before an honorable assembly in the City of London. By William Sclater, Batchelar in Divinitie, Preacher of Gods Word in the city of Exeter.</title>
            <author>Sclater, William, 1609-1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A94264</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S920</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E121_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22529</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871778</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871778</idno>
            <idno type="VID">124195</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A94264)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 124195)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 21:E121[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The remedie of schisme. Or, a mean to settle the divisions of the times. Set forth in a seasonable sermon before an honorable assembly in the City of London. By William Sclater, Batchelar in Divinitie, Preacher of Gods Word in the city of Exeter.</title>
                  <author>Sclater, William, 1609-1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 53, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Paine and M. Symmons, for Tho. Slater at the Swan in Duck-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Oct. 6".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Corinthians, 1st, II, 18-19 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Schism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:124195:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:124195:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE REMEDIE OF SCHISME.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OR,</hi> A MEAN TO SETTLE the Diviſions of the Times.</p>
            <p>Set forth in a ſeaſonable Sermon before an Honorable Aſſembly in the City of LONDON.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM SCLATER, Batchelar in Divinitie, Preacher of Gods Word in the City of <hi>Exeter.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 133.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Behold, how good, and joyfull a thing it is, for Brethren to dwell together in unity.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ROM. 16.17.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Mark them which cauſe Diviſions among you, contrary to the Doctrine which you have learned, and avoid them.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Paine,</hi> and <hi>M. Symmons,</hi> for <hi>Tho. Slater</hi> at the Swan in Duck-Lane. 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:124195:2"/>
            <head>Reader, thou muſt be entreated, for the prevention of my cenſure, e're thou read, to correct theſe following errata, which, at the firſt view pervert the ſenſe.</head>
            <p>Pag. 17. lin. 7. for his, read this. &amp; l. 28. ib. for <hi>appellatur,</hi> r. <hi>appel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letur,</hi> p. 20. l. 20. &amp; 22. for hereſie, r. hearſay. &amp; l. ib. 13. for zealous, r jealous p. 22. l. 21. for clean, r. clear. p. 23. l. 13. for, for, r. how. p. 24. l. 18. r. <hi>Bezaleel.</hi> &amp; l. 37. ib. for laſt, r. leaſt. p. 25. l. 14. for <hi>haereſcit,</hi> r. <hi>haerebit.</hi> p. 31. l. 11. for earneſt, r. Harveſt. p. 36 l. 22. for true love Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, r. true Chriſtian love. p. 46. l. 31. for ſew, r. ſow.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:124195:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONORABLE, Sir <hi>JOHN PO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LET</hi> Knight, Son and Heir to the Right Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable IOHN Lord POULET, Baron of <hi>Hinton St. George,</hi> one of the Knights of <hi>Sommerſet-ſhire</hi> for this preſent <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> The Hope of his Family, and the Honor of his Countrey, &amp;c. The Felicity of Heaven and Earth.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S it is no mean joy to your Countrey, to ſee the noble ſpirits of ancient proweſſe, and vertue, eminent in your famous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors, to ſparkle with new vigour, in your breaſt; ſo, doth it exceedingly glad me, to view the eximious and heightned Piety of your preſent Parents, (the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplarie Worthies of this Age) ſo likely to become Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, and by a ſacred <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to be tranſmigrated to po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteritie: The happy Contemplation of both which, hath anî<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated me, (the iſſue of your Father's Beneficiary) to ſhrowd this poore peece of my Theologicall Eſſayes, under your pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection: Not, that I, with <hi>Narciſſus,</hi> can ſo dote upon this off-ſpring of my own brain, as to hold it worthy of your eyes; nor that my ſhallow thoughts durſt ſwell up to ſo high ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as to think themſelves competent to deviſe a meet pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent for ſo high an acceptation; but for that your illuſtrious nobleneſſe, as a Jewels ſplendor, adding grace, and luſtre to ſome worthleſſe caſe, can ſet an eſtimate on the loweſt gift: It comes unto you, not that you (chiefly in this ſurfeit of the Preſſe) need it, but, as that Hoſpitable Prelate, <hi>Alonſo Cattilio,</hi> ſaid unto his ſteward, (complaining to him of the
<pb facs="tcp:124195:3"/>ſuperfluous number of his Followers, whom yet he ſtill meant to entertain) becauſe it needs you; under the wings of whoſe countenance, and favour, it ſhall be ſheltred, as <hi>Tiberius</hi> was by his<note n="*" place="margin">Sueton. in Tiber. ca. <hi>69.</hi>
               </note> Laurell, from all the thunderbolts of envy, or malevolence; Nor am I hopeleſſe (Honored Worthy) that your amiable candor, and known ſuavitie will vail this bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in your humble ſervant; who, (as the Queen of Sheba, heretofore, did <hi>Solomon</hi>) cannot but, (beſides my own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate notices) admire you, upon<note n="*" place="margin">1 Kin. 10.1.</note> Report; as being a known Patron of Piety, a <hi>Maecenas</hi> to Schollars, a Foe to Popery, a Champion of the Church, and a renowned Almoner to the needy: For all which, (though at ſo great a diſtance) I (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever but as an <hi>Amos</hi> among the<note n="*" place="margin">Amos 1.1.</note> Herdmen of Tekoa) can aſſure you, as the<note n="*" place="margin">Martial. l. <hi>1.</hi> Epigr. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> Poet did the great man of his Time; that the ſeverall voices of ingenuous men accord in this one har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony; Lo, a true Patriot of his Countrey.
<q>
                  <l>Vox diverſa ſonat, populorum eſt vox tamèn una,</l>
                  <l>Cùm verus patriae diceris eſſe pater.</l>
               </q> But the eximious eminency, in this kind, is ſo conſpicuous to all; that I ſhall but darken ſo blazing a Topaze, by my rude poliſhing: All I ſhall adde more, is that of<note n="*" place="margin">Plin. in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regyr.</note> 
               <hi>Pliny</hi> to <hi>Trajan, Seria te carmina, honor<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> aeternus Annalium, non haec brevis, &amp; pudenda praedicatio colet:</hi> I ſhall leave this piece, to be better blazoned by the Heralds of Time, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belliſhed in the laſting Chronicles of after Ages.</p>
            <p>What remains? but that I ſollicite, earneſtly, the throne of grace, for the accumulation of Heavens choiceſt favours, to be powred upon you; and with you, upon your vertuous Conſort, and whole noble family; to which, that together with ſo ancient, and Honorable blood, the right Religion may become equally hereditary, even untill Time it ſelf ſhall be no more, ſhall be the fervent prayers of him, who ſhall ſtrive to approve himſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>March 2. 1641.</hi>
               </date>
               <signed>Your much devoted ſervant, to be commanded, WILLIAM SCLATER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:124195:3"/>
            <head>THE REMEDIE of SCHISME.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1 COR. 11.18, 19.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For, firſt of all, when ye come together in the Church, I hear that there are diviſions among you, and I partly beleeve it: for, there muſt be alſo hereſies among you, that they which are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved may be made manifeſt among you.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Need not make Apology (Right Honor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,<note place="margin">The occaſion of this Text, why now cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen.</note> and Beloved) for this choice of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture now; when as the practiſe of too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſeems not more to be a Comment on it, than, (which all good hearts may bleed to meditate) after a ſort, indeed, an invitation to it: that expreſſion of our Saviour, on another, being alas! too true, on this occaſion;<note n="a" place="margin">Luk. 4.21.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, this day, is this Scripture fulfilled in our eares: as if that firſt<note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> enmitie ſowen by the old ſerpent, (known to the vulgar by his [cloven] foot) betwixt the two ſeeds; ſpawned in the infancie of the Creation, and nonage of the Church; ran ſtill, as tainted blood, in the veins of ſucceſſion, and ſtrove, as <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> for an ambitious<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Epiſt. Joh. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> preheminence; even in this dotage of the world; which is not, ſure,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:124195:4"/>more full of the<note n="d" place="margin">Mundus ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſcent pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur [phantaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as]; Gerſon.</note> phancy, than of moroſity, and waſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh diſcords.</p>
            <p>Lord! what unnaturall jars are here? as once between the<note n="*" place="margin">Gen. 25.22.</note> ſtrugling Twins of <hi>Rebeckah,</hi> in the ſame wombe of one, and the ſame mother, the Church: we are bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, I confeſſe, one to the other; <hi>Fratres uterini,</hi> Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, from the wombe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, having one Father, in heaven, and one mother, upon earth; (for, he who hath not the<note n="e" place="margin">Habere jam non poteſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um patrem, qui Eccleſiam non habet matrem. S. Cyprian, de unitat. Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae, Sect. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> Church, for his Mother, on earth, hath not God, for his Father, in heaven, as S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> truly) and yet, (which is not more the miſery, than the ſhame of Chriſtians) how ſeems one eſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, in affection, from another, more than ever Jews, and Samaritanes; of whom we read, in the Goſpel, that they might not<note n="f" place="margin">Ioh. 4.9.</note> converſe: as if that tender Spouſe of Gods own Son, characterized to us by her one-nes, <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.9. enblematized by that glorious Metropolis of Judea, Jeruſalem, (a City, ſaith the<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 122 3.</note> Pſalmiſt, built as one compacted, and at unity within it ſelf) had now, like <hi>Tamar,</hi> teemed an iſſue; which, as <hi>Pharez,</hi> makes rude<note n="h" place="margin">Gen. 38.29.</note> breaches through her ſides: lo! in their Muſique, nought but diviſions, and, in thoſe diviſions, endleſſe parts: <hi>Quae gens, quae regio tulit, tàm multa dictu gravia, perpeſſu aſpera, quàm hodie nos?</hi> was once the juſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of<note n="i" place="margin">Juſt. Lipſius, l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi> de Conſtant.</note> 
               <hi>Lipſius;</hi> this is a ſore grievance, and where is he, who can enough bewail it? <hi>Non enim partes ſolùm inter nos ſunt, ſed partium (ô patria, quae ſalus te ſervet?) novae partes;</hi> Our diviſions being like to a Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call line, <hi>Semper diviſibiles in ſempèr diviſibilia;</hi> or indeed, like to S. <hi>Paul's</hi> condemned Genealogies, or, King <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> daily Troubles,<note n="k" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.4.</note> endleſſe, and<note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 40.12.</note> innumerable: how much better were it for one Chriſtian with another, to be, as is obſerved of <hi>Saul,</hi> and <hi>Jonathan;</hi> who were love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and pleaſant in their lives, and in their death, they were not<note n="m" place="margin">2 Sam. 1.23.</note> divided? They ſhould not be, as that Angel, at the poole of Betheſda, who moved not, ſave onely to<note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 5.4.</note> [trouble] the waters; but rather, as thoſe Armies of them above in heaven, <hi>Revel.</hi> 19.14. of whom S. <hi>John</hi> relates, that they followed the Word, upon white
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:124195:4"/>horſes, clothed in fine linen, white, and clean; they followed, not on foot, ſaith<note n="n" place="margin">Barradius, l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>19.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord. Evang. p. <hi>447.</hi> D.</note> 
               <hi>Barradius,</hi> in a ſlow pace; but, on horſe-back, in velocity, and<note n="o" place="margin">Equus ſoli ſacer, apud Perſas, &amp; mactari ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus: in Graecos idem mos tranſlatus, ut Pauſanias ſcribit, in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conicis: qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drigae etiam eidem anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitùs dicatae, velut <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. ut verba ſunt Heliodori Aethiopic. <hi>10.</hi> — vide Selden. de Diis Syris, Syntag. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>2. 3.</hi>
               </note> ſwiftneſſe; in fine [linen], to denote the clearneſſe of their intentions, not in the [linſy-wolſy] of double mindedneſſe; in [white], the embleme of Innocence; and in [clean] linen, without the ſpots of any ſecret, or cloſe impuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; without the rents, and rags of Diviſion: for, lo! as [Armies], they troop [together], as in one band; much like to that flock of ſheep, whereto the teeth of the Spouſe are reſembled, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.2. that came up from the waſhing [even ſhorne].</p>
            <p>For this, its worth our notice, how our Saviour (who was, in prophecie, foreſtiled the<note n="p" place="margin">Iſa. 9.6.</note> 
               <hi>Prince of Peace</hi>) choſe that time, (being the eternall Word of God) to be<note n="q" place="margin">Ioh. 1.14.</note> made fleſh, and to come into the world; when as the Emperour <hi>Auguſtus</hi> ſhut up the doores of<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Plut. —vacuum du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ellis Ianum quirini clauſit, Horat. — Vide Barrad. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>16.</hi> p. <hi>43. 5.</hi> D. &amp;c. quâ ſupra.</note> 
               <hi>Janus</hi> Temple, and ſwayed the Monarchy of the world, in tranquillitie, and peace. The <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or, the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of the Angels Caroll, at his birth, was, as well Peace on earth, as Glory to God in the higheſt, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2.14. The ſubject of his Sermons, afterwards, was reſt, and peace to the weary, and troubled, <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.28. when he ſent abroad his diſciples to preach, he would not let them carry gold, nor ſilver, nor braſſe, nor ſcrip, along with them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.9. that they might not have, as S.<note n="s" place="margin">S. Ambr. ad cap. Mat. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ambroſe</hi> notes thereupon, matter of falling out in the way, no nor ſtaves, verſe the tenth, <hi>ut eriperet instrumentae ultionis,</hi> to deprive them (in caſe they ſhould differ) of a means of revenge: it was the firſt branch of their Commiſſion, into whatſoever houſe they entred, to ſay firſt, Peace be to this houſe, <hi>Luk.</hi> 10.5. <hi>Pax, quae praeſentes ſociat, abſentes invitat,</hi> in the gloſſe of<note n="t" place="margin">Chryſolog. ſer <hi>138.</hi> p. <hi>586.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chryſologus;</hi> Peace, which is the glue, or ſoder, to conjoyn men preſent; Peace. which is the load ſtone, to draw men abſent: in ſhort, peace was that legacie, which he (as the map of the whole world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of his other favours) bequeathed, on his laſt Will, and Teſtament, to his deare diſciples; ſaying, <hi>Peace I
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:124195:5"/>leave with you, my peace I give unto you,</hi> Joh. 14.27. After his Reſurrection, finding them together, he came, and ſtood in the midſt amongſt them, and ſaid, <hi>Peace be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you,</hi> Luk. 24.36. This was Chriſts practiſe: And now, as S.<note n="u" place="margin">S. Bern. me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. &amp; S. Cyp. l. de zelo. &amp; livore, Sect. <hi>10.</hi> Chriſti [no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men] induere, &amp; non per Chriſti [viam] pergere, quid aliud, quam praevaricatio eſt divini no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minis?</note> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> excellently, <hi>Operae pretium eſt, ut, ſicùt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus haeredes nominis, ita ſimus &amp; imitatores ſanctitatis;</hi> Its very meet, that as we all inherit the name, ſo ſhould we alſo imitate the ſanctitie of Chriſt, ſutably unto that of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it is convenient, not onely to be [called] but (that which alone can render us truly happy) to [be] Chriſtians: and, as it was ſaid of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> and <hi>Soſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> (two, who were nearly related) whoſe profeſſions correſponded not unto their Names; for, the one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prizing, in his Name, an horſe, the other, a man; The firſt of theſe, <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> was a great Phyſitian, and cured men; the ſecond, <hi>Soſander,</hi> skilled better, to cure horſes; which thing a third obſerving; for ſhame, ſirs, ſaid he,<note n="w" place="margin">Plutarch.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, either change your names, or alter your profeſſions: For this, that good Emperour <hi>Theodoſius</hi> finding one <hi>Demophilus,</hi> a Chriſtian, and a Prelate, to be [contentious], told him plainly; <hi>Si tu pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem fugis, ego te ab Eccleſiâ fugere mando;</hi> If thou flie peace, I'le make thee flie the Church: Our Apoſtle here, verſe the ſixteenth of this Chapter, well aſſured him, that, if any man did ſeem [<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> contentious], the Church of God [had] not, ſurely, [ought not] to have any ſuch Cuſtome; and good reaſon, for if the thorns of ſtrife be ſuffered to grow up once among them; no marvell, if all thriving, by the means of grace, be<note n="*" place="margin">Matth. 13.22.</note> choaked in them.</p>
            <p>And indeed, the main ſcope of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> in this text, is conceived to be,<note place="margin">The ſcope of the Text.</note> an acquainting the Corinthians of the cauſe of their non proficiencie by the means of grace; and what the Reaſon was, that, when they came together, in the Church, to partake the Supper of the Lord; yet they were ſtill the worſe, for that holy, and ſalutiferous banquet, <hi>ver.</hi> 17. Now, the [cauſe], and withall, the [ſigne] of that miſcarriage, were thoſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtine
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:124195:5"/>diſcords, and thoſe ill-hearing diviſions, that' as ſome broken ulcers, or the running iſſues of an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtumated body, he had heard to be both raiſed up, and too much fomented among them, <hi>ver.</hi> 18. And the ſpeciall inducement, that led the Apoſtle, and father of their faith unto a likelihood, that his credulitie of that report was not wholly uncharitable was founded upon ſomething [greater], that, of neceſſitie, [muſt] be in the Church; and that was hereſie: For, if hereſies, which are the [greater] evil, [muſt] be; then ſchiſms, and diviſions [may] be; but hereſies [muſt] be; proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it was therefore alſo, that diviſions might be; For, ſo we read, Firſt. of all, <hi>When ye come together in the Church, I hear that there are diviſions among you, and I partly beleeve it; For, there muſt be alſo hereſies among you, &amp;c.</hi> And thus, as in a Landskip, ye have ſeen both the ayme, and the <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of my Text; which by the key of Analyticall reaſon, may be unlocked, and opened into a gallery, which leadeth us into two moſt faire, and ſpatious roomes; plainly, it may be reſolved into theſe two generall parts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. An Imputation, <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. That there were divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions among them.<note place="margin">The Diviſion of the Text.</note>
               </item>
               <item>2. The Ground, or Reaſon of that Imputation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there muſt be hereſies.</item>
            </list>
            <p>The former of theſe, however I need not divide, (for that the words be, in themſelves, alreadie full of diviſions) yet, for order ſake, I herein obſerve theſe part culars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The Crime it ſelf imputed, There were diviſions.</item>
               <item>2. The place, where, or, the Company among whom they aroſe; in the Church, and, among you.</item>
               <item>3. The mean of Information, by which S. <hi>Paul</hi> came to know it, <hi>Heareſay.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. The Meaſure of his Credulity, upon that <hi>Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay, He partly beleeved it.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In the latter, we have
<list>
                  <item>1. The nature of hereſies, what they are.</item>
                  <item>2. The neceſſitie of hereſies, how they muſt be.</item>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:124195:6"/>
                  <item>3. The place of hereſies, where they ariſe.</item>
                  <item>4. The uſe, or end of hereſies, why they are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in the Church of God.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe are the parts; in which, as in a peece of Arras diſplayed, I have ſhewed you the ſeverall pictures fold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up in this Scripture: which, (were it happily in a skilfuller hand) might yet be branch't out farther, and embroydered into more varietie, as ſome rich piece of Tyſſue, wrought full of Demonſtrations: But, even thus we ſee, how this little<note n="a" place="margin">1 King. 18.44.</note> cloud of words, which in the firſt view, was but as that ſeen by <hi>Elijah's</hi> ſervant, to be ſpanned by an hand, is now wombd-out, as t'were, and ſwollen into ſuller bottels; ready, (as King <hi>Davia's</hi> plentifull<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 68.9.</note> rain), to be diſtilled; and to drop down into the eares, and hearts of you (the Lords in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance) to refreſh them: In ſumme, ye have ſeen the meaſures of my Sermon, and you Noble patience; daigne to favour me with the one, whileſt I am, by Gods bleſſing, in the diſpatch of the other; I ſhall be as compendious, as the majeſtie of the ſubject ſhall allow, in all: may the ſame hand, that gave this opportunity, adde alſo a ſucceſſe to this buſineſſe: <hi>For, firſt of all, when ye come together in the Church, I hear that there are diviſions among you, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt of theſe particulars,<note place="margin">The firſt part.</note> the Crime imputed to theſe Corinth's charge, to wit, diviſions; how gladly could I wiſh them all from being the too-juſt occaſion of my preſent diſcourſe; ſurely my deſires are to have them ſundred from all our practice, farther than the Eaſt is from the Weſt; and that the two ends of a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter might as ſoon meet, or, the two poles be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled! But, ſith the<note n="c" place="margin">Rev. 12.12.</note> ſhortneſſe of Satan's kingdom hath made him double his malice, and more exaſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the<note n="d" place="margin">Eph. 2.2.</note> children of diſobedience, in whom he rules, unto diſſentions; I ſhall be forced to ſay ſomething of them; and that, <hi>Non exclamantis ſtudio, ſed dolentis af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectu;</hi> Not, out of any deſire I have, to declaim on the diſtempers of the Age, but rather to declare my zealous ſorrow for them: though, were I as <hi>Jeremy,</hi> who is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:124195:6"/>noted to have been <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, moſt full of paſſion; or, as <hi>S. Gregory</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">S. Gregor. Nazianz. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. p. <hi>2.</hi> Eton ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſ.</note> 
               <hi>Nazianzene</hi> ſaith of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> that he was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of a loftie, and a bigge ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion; yea, if I ſhould lay <hi>Pelion</hi> upon <hi>Oſſa,</hi> and make even mountains of expreſſions; or, had more than <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſelah,</hi> even a breath like eternitie; yet were I never able, to ſet forth this evill, and this crying ſin of the times; either full, or lowd, or long enough: however, I have reſolved, with that poore<note n="f" place="margin">Mar. 12.42.</note> widow, to caſt in a little, though but a mite, or two.</p>
            <p>And, as that<note n="g" place="margin">Luk. 15.8.</note> woman in the Goſpel, firſt lighted up her candle, ere ſhe ſought her groat; I ſhall, firſt, ſay ſomewhat of the name; and, after that, of the thing it ſelf; according to that rule of the Stoique <hi>Epictetus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>The word, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, tranſlated, in the Text, diviſions,<note place="margin">The nature of Schiſme ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained.</note> comes of a Greek originall, derived <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the generall notion thereof, ſignifying any rent, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union, or ſeparation of things combined, and united together; ſo, <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.16. <hi>If a new piece be put into an old garment,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>the ſchiſme; or the rent is made worſe:</hi> Its from bodily things tranſlated, metapho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rically, to denote diſunion of minds, and affections; ſo<note n="*" place="margin">Iſidor. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> Etymol.</note> 
               <hi>Iſidore, Nomen Schiſmatis â ſciſſurâ [animorum] eſt:</hi> and thus, in a latitude of ſenſe, (according to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſitie of the contrary unions) it hath a various accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. There is conſent, there is concord, there is peace; each differ from other: Conſent we call unity in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Concord, unity of will, and deſire; Peace, quiet, and calme converſation, a life void of janglings, and free from tumults: There may be conſent, without concord; there may be concord, without conſent; there may be peace, without both; that is to ſay, men may agree in their opinion, and yet differ in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires; they may diſſent in opinion, and deſires, and yet live in peace; S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Barnabas;</hi> S. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and <hi>Hierome,</hi> were of different judgements; yet brake not out into publique, or any notorious violations of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: This premiſed, ſchiſme ſometimes denotes, at
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:124195:7"/>large, [any] diſunion in judgement, or opinion, in will, or affections; but, more ſtrictly, it ſignifieth ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from the [unity] of the Church of God, as<note n="h" place="margin">Thom. <hi>2.2.</hi> qu. <hi>39.</hi> Art. <hi>1.</hi> in Corp. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Dr. Feild, li. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>5. of the Church.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Aquinas</hi> exactly; whether the diſunion be inward, in minde, or affection; or outward, in externall ſociety, and communion: When the kingdom of Iſrael (which, under <hi>David,</hi> was one Politique, and civill Body) was, afterwards, parted, and divided, twixt <hi>Rehoboam,</hi> and <hi>Jeroboam;</hi> that was a civill Schiſme, a rent made in the Politique Body; when Jews, and Samaritanes were ſo far dworced in affections, that they endured no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce each with other; that was a ſchiſme grown, upon point of Religion: Again, there is, ſaith<note n="i" place="margin">Pet. Martyr, loc. com. elaſſ. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>6</hi> Sect. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> a double ſchiſme, <hi>Bonum, &amp; malum;</hi> a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable, and lawfull; a criminall, and a ſinfull ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: of the firſt ſort was that of faithfull <hi>Abraham,</hi> when he ſeparated from the Idolatrous Aſtrologers of Chaldea; It is, when the unity, that is broken, is evill, then the diviſion is good: on the other ſide, when the unity is good, the ſeparation is evil: Its evil unity, that is in evill, and that criminall unity is forbidden; <hi>Simeon,</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> were brethren in iniquity; into their ſecret, let not my ſoul enter, ſaith good <hi>Iacob, Gen.</hi> 49.6. To the ſame purpoſe, King <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 1.10. <hi>My ſonne, if ſinners entice thee, conſent thou not;</hi> for, even bryars and thorns will be twiſting one in the other, and ſhall, at laſt be bound up together, in bundles, for the fire.</p>
            <p>And indeed, ſaith a reverend<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Biſh</hi> Morton, Grand impoſt. c. <hi>15.</hi> theſ. <hi>4.</hi> Sect. <hi>26.</hi>
               </note> Father of our Church; amongſt men there are many unjuſt unities: there is <hi>Vnio Leonina,</hi> an union of compulſion, and terror; there is <hi>unio vulpina,</hi> a combination of craft, and cunning; there is <hi>unio Aſinina,</hi> an union of ſimplicity, or ſillineſſe, when poore <hi>Ignaro's</hi> hang together; but onely as crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that follow in the drove, not knowing whither they are hurried: our Romaniſts boaſt much of their Unity, or conſent in Doctrine; yeeld it to be as great, as may be; but whileſt it is, by<note n="*" place="margin">See Biſhop <hi>Hall, Dec.</hi> 6. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 4.</note> conſequent, [<note n="*" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Sclat.</hi> on 1 <hi>Theſ. p.</hi> 201.</note> againſt] the Goſpel, it is no note of the Church; even in hell is a kinde of unity,<note n="l" place="margin">Matth. 12.25</note> Satan is not divided againſt himſelf:
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:124195:7"/>True union we call onely that, which is onely in Gods truth, and for Truth's ſake; otherwiſe, as S.<note n="m" place="margin">Hilar. Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctav. l. ad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan. Auguſt. — <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Iſido. Peluſiot. li. <hi>3.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>246.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hilary</hi> ſaith, <hi>Per ſpecioſum pacis nomen, in unitatem perfidiae ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repimus;</hi> it is not union of faith, but of perfidiouſneſſe, nor Chriſtian communion, but Antichriſtian conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie, and conjuration: There was an union among the body of the ten Tribes, in the worſhip of <hi>Ieroboam's</hi> idolatrous Calves; They, who under <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> and <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah,</hi> ſeparated from that ſociety, and joyned with Gods people, in the pure worſhip at Jeruſalem; their ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was good, for the unity was evill: There was in the Church of Rome, (after that<note n="n" place="margin">Vide Fran. Maſon. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi> p. <hi>167.</hi> nu. <hi>7.</hi> de Miniſter. Anglicano.</note> Bethel, by a filthie degenerating, became a Bethaven) an unity, or conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie rather, in damnable errour: <hi>Luther,</hi> (whom yet <hi>Albertus Crantzius</hi> adviſed rather unto a praying [for] than to the hopes [of] a reformation) he, with his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents, was by them condemned for ſchiſme, becauſe they ſeparated; howbeit their ſeparation was holy, for the unity was evill: Now, on the other ſide, crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſchiſme is, when the unity is good, and in things good, commanded, or permitted; yea, though it be with evill men, warily underſtood: ſo our Saviour himſelf, and his diſciples, communicated with Scribes, and Phariſees, in the ſacrifices, and other ſervices of the Temple, the [things] themſelves were good, and commanded; though ſome of the [perſons] evill, that uſed them: hence that Maxime, in Theology, <hi>Bonitas Miniſtri non eſt de eſſentiâ Sacramenti, ſed de convenientiâ,</hi> as<note n="o" place="margin">Rayner, de Piſis, tom. <hi>1.</hi> Pantheolog. c. <hi>4.</hi> de Baptiſm. p. <hi>210. 211.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Raynerius</hi> hath it; the goodneſſe, in theſe holy things, dependeth on the vertue of Gods own imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate inſtitution, and his divine ordination; not, on the dignitie of the perſon, whoſoever adminiſters them; though indeed, the pietie, and devotion of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter be a great [convenience] to the ordinance it ſelf; for, we read how, (through the miſpriſion of the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar) for the lewd converſation of <hi>Eli's</hi> ſons, the verie<note n="p" place="margin">1. Sam. 2.12.</note> ſacrifice it ſelf began to be abhorred: and yet, the ſpot of an impure hand cannot diſcolour the beautie of Gods myſteries; no more, ſaith S. <hi>Gregory</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">S. Greg. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zian. Orat. <hi>40.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nazianzene,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:124195:8"/>than the image of an Emperor, cut with art, in a ſignet, whether of gold, or iron, can, by its impreſſion, alter the matter, or the nature of the wax, upon which its ſtamped.</p>
            <p>There is, in the Church of Rome, reteined<note n="*" place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> now Biſhop of Worceſter, Serm. ſtiled <hi>[Epheſus back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding] p.</hi> 12. on Revel. 2.4.</note> truth, in ſundrie Articles of faith, as, of the Trinitie, of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, &amp;c. Its no hereſie, to conform in judgement, no not with thoſe very Antichriſtians, where they conſent in truth: In the Church of <hi>England,</hi> we have (God be bleſſed) purity of ſound doctrine, and of the worſhip of God; what, if ſome unſound for their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular perſons, communicate with us herein? ſhall we, as Brownifts,<note n="r" place="margin">Ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> propter [paleam] re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquam [are<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am] Domini, nec propter piſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es malos rumpimus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia Domini, non enim pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter malos bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni deſerendi. ſed propter bonos mali to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerandi ſunt —ſicut tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raverunt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetae, &amp;c. S. Auguſt. epiſt. <hi>48.</hi>—confer <hi>Bp:</hi> Hall, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy <hi>againſt</hi> Browniſts, Sect. <hi>4.</hi> &amp;, <hi>7.23.33.57.</hi> ib.</note> ſeparate? we may be preſent with them, after that rule of S. <hi>Proſper, Spe correctionis, non conſenſu malignitatis;</hi> in hope to amend them, out of the love of compaſſion; not to allow their malignity, by an erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous approbation: Hold faith with the worſt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique, where his faith is ſound; not indeed, I confeſſe, for the ſake of the heretique, but meerly for the love of the faith: hold worſhip with the worſt Idolater, where (for that Act) the worſhip is pure; Communion in word, in Sacraments, in Prayers, with worſt men; for, herein the unity is good, the things themſelves being allowed, and commanded by God; therefore the ſchiſme, or the ſeparation were evill: Even <hi>Rome,</hi> is a<note n="*" place="margin">Calvin. li <hi>4</hi> ca. <hi>2.</hi> Sect. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> Church ſtill, ſaith <hi>Calvin,</hi> but a beaſtly Harlot, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxicated, and grown mad with fornications; we<note n="ſ" place="margin">See Biſhop <hi>Morton, c.</hi> 15. <hi>Grand Impoſt. Sect.</hi> 24. of the true cauſes of our ſeparation from <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </note> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake her not, in what conſtitutes a Church, (namely, the Word, and Sacraments) but in her filthy errors, and corruptions: Let her leave her whoring with ſtrange fleſh, and with ſtrange gods; (for, whileſt ſhe followeth ſuch<note n="t" place="margin">Ion. 2.8.</note> lying vanities, ſhe forſaketh her own mercy) and then<note n="u" place="margin">[Fugati] po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, quam [fugientes], â Româ corruptâ ſeceſſimus; iterùm, ſi ſanari velir, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſuri ad eam, ut ad ſororem: vide D. Prideaux Lectur. <hi>9.</hi> Sect. <hi>17.</hi> de Viſibil. Eccleſ. — confer Franc. Maſon. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. &amp;c. <hi>13.</hi> quâ ſupra: — Item, Petr. Martyr. loc. com. claſſ <hi>4</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> Sect. <hi>48.</hi> — &amp; cap. <hi>20.</hi> ib. — Item, Zanchium, ca. <hi>8.</hi> de Eccleſia, inter Miſcellan. &amp; alios, &amp;c.</note> [ſo far] as ſhe keeps cloſe to Chriſt, and to that firſt, ancient, and pure faith, (ſo famous, in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:124195:8"/>S. <hi>Paul's</hi> daies, that it was mounted on the wings of honour, and carried throughout the<note n="w" place="margin">Rom. 1.8.</note> world) ſo farre, we ſhall not refuſe to give her an hand of fellowſhip; But, till then, the danger of familiarity may be leſſe, in a Peſt-houſe: For, ever ſince the fountains of pure wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters failed upon the ſeven hils; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the<note n="x" place="margin">Theocrit.</note> Poet hath it, this grape is grown to a dry raiſin; yea, ſhe hath pitched her Tents, <hi>in Campo Martio,</hi> and turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Religion into quarrell; and, much like to thoſe <hi>Galli ſenones,</hi> of old, whom<note n="y" place="margin">Luc. Florus, l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi> Hiſt.</note> 
               <hi>Florus</hi> writes of, to be ſo full of crueltie, <hi>Vt planè nati ad hominum interitum, &amp; ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium ſtragem videantur;</hi> that they ſeem to have been born for deſtruction, not of Cities onely, but of ſouls. Wherefore,<note n="z" place="margin">Apoc. 18.4.</note> come out of this whoriſh Babylon, my people, ſaith the Lord, ſeparate, leſt, by partaking in her ſins, ye ſhare alſo in her plagues; for it is become the very ſink of filthineſſe.</p>
            <p>To ſhut up this point; we muſt remember, that what is thus ſpoken, for matter of faith, and doctrine, holds alſo (rightly underſtood) for outward Rites, and Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of order, and decency, in the Church of God: In thoſe rites, that are not ſimply unlawfull, there is a lawfull unity; there may be, yea, there is, oft times an unlawfull ſeparation; ſo the Schoolmen define, Schiſme to be, [<note n="b" place="margin">Nicolaus de Orbellis, Diſt. <hi>13.</hi> qu. <hi>6.</hi> in quart. Sent.</note> 
               <hi>illicitus</hi>] <hi>diſceſſus,</hi> an [unlawfull] de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture from the unity of the Church: If any abuſe a Rite, (indifferent in it ſelf, and innocent) with a ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious, or perhaps idolatrous intention, [that] is their foule ſin: May not another uſe the [ſame] indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent things, for decencie, and order-ſake onely; if that he do not uſe them [ſo], as thoſe ſinners did? We may do [<note n="c" place="margin">Dr. Sclater, p. <hi>276.</hi> &amp; p. <hi>392. on 1. Theſſalon.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>eadem</hi>], but not <hi>[ità]; Turpis est omnis pars, quae univerſo non congruit ſuo,</hi> as S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> expreſly.</p>
            <p>And indeed, the very proper, adequate, and full ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, about which Shciſme is converſant, is, critically, matter of<note n="d" place="margin">Via. Lambert Danaeum, in Proleg<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. ad S. Auguſt. lib. de. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>ſ. p. <hi>12.</hi> &amp;c. —</note> rite, &amp; circumſtance; as both Fathers, School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and the moſt judicious Moderns, (with whom I have conſulted herein) joyntly accord; ſchiſme, in this verſe, differing from hereſie, in the next; in this; <hi>viz.</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:124195:9"/>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Schiſmaticus eſt, ſacrilegâ diſceſſione; Haereticus, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilego dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate: <hi>S.</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> cont. Gaudent. &amp; l. <hi>9.</hi> Evang. ſecund. Matth. — confer Pet. Martyr, qua ſupra, Sect. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>789.</hi> — &amp; Fr. Maſon. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi> p. <hi>161. 163.</hi>—Item, Alex Hales. part. <hi>2.</hi> qu <hi>164.</hi> &amp; Thom. 2a. 2ae. qu. <hi>36.</hi>— &amp; Kelliſon, a Papiſt, l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> Sect. <hi>5.</hi> Survey of the new Relig. &amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lios.</note> ſchiſme, is a breach of unity, in point of diſcipline, and of the external worſhip of God; hereſie, is a corruption, through new, and falſe opinions, (as may appear here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after) of the ſinceritie of faith, and of ſound doctrine.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, for the cloſe of this part, and the clear ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the Text; we muſt diſtinguiſh Schiſme, thus explained, into its kinds, or degrees: The one is inchoate onely, or partiaty, the other, pertinacious and conſummate: The firſt is, when the diviſion ſtaies in judgement, or affection alone, proceeding not ſo farre, as actuall ſeparation; or, if ſo, its from private, and friendly familiarity onely; not compleate, or ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinate diſunion from the publique communion in the worſhip of God: And of this partiary nature was the ſchiſme, now charged by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> upon theſe Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, in the Text; and this too, to be meant, not of the whole Body of the Church of Corinth, at large; (for [that] he commended highly, for conforming un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his ordinances delivered unto them, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2.) but, as <hi>Calvin, Cornelius â lapide,</hi> and<note n="f" place="margin">Pet. Martyr. claſſ. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> Sect. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>741.</hi>
               </note> other judicious affirm,) of ſome particular ſtraglers, juſtly to be reproved.</p>
            <p>And thus farre, of the explication of the nature of Schiſme, the crime imputed by the Apoſtle, on this Church of Corinth: <hi>First of all, when ye come together in the Church, I hear that there are [diviſions] among you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next particular is the place,<note place="margin">The ſecond part.</note> where, or, if you will, the company, among whom, theſe ſchiſmes, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions aroſe; and that was, <hi>In the Church;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>When ye come together in the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Divines, of ſeverall judgements, give us a ſeverall interpetation of this paſſage:<note n="g" place="margin">Beza, ad locum.</note> 
               <hi>Beza,</hi> and thoſe of his way, will have it meant, <hi>de ſacro conventu;</hi> or, as ſome<note n="h" place="margin">Vide Gou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lartinus, An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notat, ad S. Cyprian. l. de Eleemoſyn. num. <hi>32.</hi>
               </note> others, to the ſame effect, expreſſe it, <hi>De Caetu fidelium,</hi> onely of the company of the faithfull, who make up the myſticall Church of Chriſt; underſtanding the words, not of the [place], but of the [perſons], who, as thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as S. <hi>Peter</hi> cals them, as<note n="i" place="margin">1. Pet. 2.5.</note> living ſtones build up the ſpirituall houſe of God; Chriſt himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the chief ſtone of the<note n="k" place="margin">Eph, 2.20.</note> corner: And, in this ſence
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:124195:9"/>alone, the now renowned Paſtor, and Reader of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinitie, in <hi>Geneva,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Freder. Span<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemius epiſt. Dedic.</hi> 3. <hi>part. Dub. Evang. Ann.</hi> 1638. — But ſince the preaching of this Sermon. I perceive, that ſome would make him, in this true [Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion], to ſpeak onely a [complement] as if an irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragable truth had ſtood in need of ſo poore an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe.</note> 
               <hi>Fredericus Spanhemius,</hi> (he, who, though onely as a looker on, and as it were aloofe, bleſſeth God for thoſe eminent graces, that have, in all ages, ſince the Goſpel, ſhined in the eximious Biſhops of this Church) he, I ſay, if we may take it upon truſt, will have the word [<note n="*" place="margin">See the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, Act. 19.39, 40.</note> Church], to be no otherwiſe meant, in the new Teſtament.</p>
            <p>But yet, <hi>Theophylact,</hi> and all Greek Writers, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally expound it, in this Text, of the materiall place of meeting; where the Saints of Corinth uſually aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled together, for receiving of the Sacrament, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſacred, and religious performances.</p>
            <p>If we take it, in this latter<note n="*" place="margin">Vbi procul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dubio, Eccleſiae nomen [locum] quo Eccleſia congregatur, fignificat. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantus, de Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus Eccleſ. Cathol. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> ſenſe; as indeed S. <hi>Paul,</hi> by <hi>ver.</hi> 20. ſeemeth to interpret it; ſaying, (with the very ſame relations) <hi>When ye come together,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which both, in <hi>Act.</hi> 2.1. and here, is, by the <hi>Genevians</hi> themſelves, rendred, in their own Bible, by [into one, and the ſame [<note n="*" place="margin">See 1 Cor. 14 23.</note> place]: and <hi>ver.</hi> 22. taking the abuſe of the [Church], by their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or banquets, (though of love); he ſeemeth to contra-diſtinguiſh it unto their own<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>So verſe 34.</hi> If any man hunger, let him eat, at [home.]</note> houſes of habitation; which were much more meet for feaſting, and entertainment, than the Church, a place conſecrate, and ſet apart for onely ſacred, and divine refreſhments; whereof that of eating the Lords Supper was a principall: Thus if we interpret it, of the place, we may note; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>
               </label> That, in the very infancy of the Chriſtian Church, Gods people had places of ſolemne meeting, for the joynt-diſcharge of their devotions: in <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.25. this ſame Apoſtle excites them, to a fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentation of their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or aſſembling of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves together, by which<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſtius, ad</hi> Heb. 10.25.</note> 
               <hi>Estius</hi> himſelf confeſſeth, the Greek Expoſitors to have relation to ſome places of Gods worſhip, where theſe Saints ſhould meet, and come together.</p>
            <p>I know its quaered among the learned, whether, till the daies of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, namely, about 300. yeers from Chriſt, the Chriſtians had any Churches built up, or not? That which gave hint to the dubita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:124195:10"/>is that known objection of Heathens, againſt thoſe Chriſtians, who laboured to convert them, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant in <hi>Minutius Felix,</hi> and other Ancients; <hi>Non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betis Templa, non Altaria;</hi> They had no temples, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to worſhip that God inviſible, whom, they ſaid, they ſerved? For anſwer, its moſt certain; that, in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles dayes, beſides the Temple of Jeruſalem; (which ſtood, till <hi>Titus,</hi> and <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> the Romane Emperors, ſurprized, and waſted it, nigh 40. yeers from Chriſt, as<note n="n" place="margin">Joſephus, li. <hi>7.</hi> belli Judai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci, confer Cent. <hi>1.</hi> li. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Joſephus</hi> calculates);<note n="o" place="margin">Euſeb. l. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi> &amp; Polydo. Virg. li. de In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent. rerum. c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> open, garniſhed Churches they had none; becauſe the very name of Chriſtianity was ſo odious to the Emperours of thoſe dayes, and (to uſe the language of that time,) that [Sect] ſo everie where ſpoken againſt, <hi>Act.</hi> 28.22. that, in ſtead of being (as they ſhould have been)<note n="p" place="margin">Iſa. 49.23.</note> nurſing Fathers unto the Church, they proved rather, as Wolves, to fright, yea, to dilaniate, and teare in pieces the flock of Chriſt: <hi>Nero,</hi> he began the fray, and was, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſtiles him,<note n="q" place="margin">Tertul. ca. <hi>5.</hi> Apologet.</note> 
               <hi>Dedicator damnationis;</hi> unto him ſucceeded <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitian,</hi> and ſo the reſt of thoſe ſcarlet Tyrants, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, untill the times of <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> and <hi>Maximian,</hi> who rid the Empire with more looſe reignes, than ſome others of the ſormer did; and with rowels of [longer] crueltie, as <hi>Euſebius,</hi> and <hi>Eutropius</hi> inform us, ſo ſpurred the ſides, yea, gored the very bowels of it; that, except they meant to found a Church in blood, they could not build: But, when there were (as God was pleaſed to dart ſome gleames of eaſe through the blackeſt cloud of perſecution) ſome <hi>Lucida intervalla</hi> opened; they re-attempted the ſame work: ſo<note n="r" place="margin">Rodolph. Hoſpin. de O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigin. Templor. part. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian</hi> aſſures us, that, under <hi>Severus, Gordianus, Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus,</hi> and <hi>Galienus,</hi> Churches began to be erected by Chriſtians; (for what Ethniques called <hi>Templa,</hi> ſaith<note n="s" place="margin">Pamelius, in Annot. ad S. Cyprian, li. de Eleemoſyn. num. <hi>32.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pamelius,</hi> Chriſtians ſtiled<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Hooker l. <hi>5.</hi> p. <hi>205.</hi> Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſt, Polity, <hi>and Sir</hi> Hen. Spelman.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) but they were ſoon again demoliſhed by <hi>Diocleſian:</hi> At length, that famous Chriſtian Emperour, (with whoſe birth our<note n="v" place="margin">Baronius, An. <hi>306.</hi> nu. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> Britaine was enobled), <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, as an Orient ſtarre aroſe; and he, not onely as a Phyſitian, to heale the wounds of the Saints themſelves; but alſo, as a Repairer
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:124195:10"/>of the breaches, made, by foregoing Tyrants, in the places of their ſolemrie meeting. Not, but that they had [before], <hi>Conventicula,</hi> as<note n="w" place="margin">Arnobius, l. <hi>4.</hi> contra Gent. verſus finem.</note> 
               <hi>Arnobius</hi> cals them, <hi>in quibus ſummus oratur Deus;</hi> they had <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Euſeb. li.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 1.2.3.</note> 
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſtiles them; that is, places of coming together, Oratories, and houſes of worſhip, to perform the rites of their Religion in; But, all this time, thoſe houſes were more humble, than magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent: Beauty being the badge of opulency, and<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>See my Lo. Primate of</hi> Armagh, l. <hi>9.</hi> Sect. <hi>17.</hi> de Succeſſione Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Chriſt.</note> orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of proſperity.</p>
            <p>All which I have obſerved, on this occaſion, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe, how welcome joynt-devotion hath ever been unto the God we ſerve; <hi>The effectuall, fervent prayer of a righteous man,</hi> though but one alone, <hi>availeth [much],</hi> Jam. 5.16. but, when two, or three, a [number] meet together, in one place of worſhip, and thoſe alſo <hi>[una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimitèr] orantes,</hi> as S.<note n="z" place="margin">S. Cyprian. l. de Vnit. Eccle. Sect. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cyprian</hi> gloſſeth on it; praying in unity, and unanimity; variety of hearts, and voices making up one ſweet conſort, and harmony of devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; lo! ſaith<note n="a" place="margin">Thom. 1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.2<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. qu. <hi>102.</hi> Art. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Aquinas, orationes ibi fiunt magis [exau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibiles], ex devotione orantium;</hi> The prayers become [more audible] in the eares of God, yea, it bringeth down the Lord from heaven, after a ſort, into the very midſt among them, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.20.</p>
            <p>We then, my brethren, enjoying more open free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and ampler beauty, (though indeed, as S.<note n="b" place="margin">S. Bern. de Templo, fol. <hi>110.</hi> G. Deus magis diligit puras mentes, quàm ſuperau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratos parietes.</note> 
               <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> truly,<note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 93.5.</note> inward holineſſe becometh beſt the houſe of [that] God, <hi>Qui non tàm politis marmoribus, quàm or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natis moribus delectatur,</hi> who is more delighted with the ornament of moralitie, than with the beſt<note n="d" place="margin">Pſa. 144.12</note> poliſhed corners of an outward Temple) we, I ſay, obteining more libertie of acceſſe unto the places of Gods publike worſhip, which our primitive forefathers<note n="e" place="margin">See Heb. 11.38.</note> wanted: though their zeal to build up Churches, and to endow them too, out-ran ours, as <hi>Ahimaaz</hi> did <hi>Cuſhi,</hi> for they went by the way of the [<note n="f" place="margin">2 Sam. 18.23.</note> plain]; they being, like <hi>Iacob,</hi> under the old Teſtament,<note n="g" place="margin">Gen. 25.27.</note> [plain] men; unacquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the dark Meanders of cunning, and deceive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſſe; oh let not us neglect the means of our ſo
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:124195:11"/>great ſalvation; nor forſake the aſſembling of our ſelves together, in the places of Gods holy worſhip, as the manner of ſome was, even in S. <hi>Paul's</hi> time, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.25.</p>
            <p>And, when we do<note n="*" place="margin">See Eccleſ. 5.2.1.</note> approach that place, where the Lord profeſſeth, that, in a ſpeciall manner, his<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 26.8.</note> honour dwelleth; let us ſay, as old <hi>Iacob</hi> did of Bethel, <hi>Quàm reverenda ſunt haec loca!</hi> Gen. 28.17. ſurely, the Lord is in this place, and how dreadfull is it? this is none other but the houſe of God, and this is the gate of heaven. Such holy meditations would make us all abhor that ſwiniſh hereſie of the Fratricellians, who, as<note n="i" place="margin">Turrecremata li. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>11.</hi> &amp; <hi>37.</hi> do Eccleſ.</note> 
               <hi>Turre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cremata</hi> ſaith, aſſerted, <hi>Eccleſiam non plus valere ad oran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, quàm Porcorum ſtabulum;</hi> that a Church was of no more eſteeme, or value for devotion, than was a ſwine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie; an opinion beſt ſuting to the devotion of the bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Author: This meditation alſo would make our ſtomackes riſe againſt that ſacrilegious thought of all thoſe cruell Edomites, that cry out nothing, but,<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 137.7.</note> 
               <hi>Down with them, down with them, even to the ground:</hi> yea rather, we ſhould, with that man,<note n="l" place="margin">1. Sam. 13.14.</note> after Gods own heart, be<note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 122.1.</note> glad, and rejoyce, when we go up to the houſe of the Lord; And, when we are there, to pray for grace, to the<note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 65.2.</note> hearer of prayer, in that<note n="o" place="margin">Matt. 21.13.</note> Houſe of prayer, to ſerve God acceptably, with<note n="p" place="margin">Heb. 12.28.</note> reverence, and godly fear: which ſervice of ſo [great] a God, we ſhall then, indeed, make moſt acceptable; when, as<note n="q" place="margin">Ignatius, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. ad Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.</note> 
               <hi>Ignatius,</hi> in much zeal ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted his Magneſians, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, we do all joyntly together, as one man; or, as <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> to the Sepulchre, run<note n="r" place="margin">Ioh. 20.4.</note> [together] in unity, to the houſe of the Lord: our coming toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, otherwiſe, into one place, may prove, like to that of theſe Corinthians, in the 17. verſe of this Chapter, <hi>not for the better, but for the worſe;</hi> namely, becauſe there were [diviſions] among them, even in the very [Church] it ſelf; for ſo is the Text, <hi>Firſt of all, when ye come together in the [Church], I hear that there are [divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions] among you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus much hath been ſpoken of this [Church,]
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:124195:11"/>in the Text, as the Greek Expoſitors underſtand it, of the [place] of Gods worſhip.</p>
            <p>Now, if we interpret it, with other learned Divines, not, of the place; but, of the [perſon] even of the company of the faithfull,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> called into the unity of one faith, by one Goſpel, and one Spirit; and that, among his company, in this Church of God, (called, and<note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.2.</note> ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified, as theſe Corinth's were) there were Schiſmes, and Diviſion, found; we may note; <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>
               </label> That particular Schiſmes, and Diviſions may conſiſt with a true, and ſolid Church of God: ſo we read, verſe the ſecond of this Chapter, that the main body of theſe Corinthians were applauded, for their conformity, unto the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances delivered unto them, by the Apoſtle, though ſome few, it ſeems, had, by ſome private janglings, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up a faction among them: wherefore, we muſt conceive him, after his Chriſtian charity, to angle out the offenders by themſelves; and not to involve the whole, promiſcuouſly, in the devouring drag net of a mercileſſe cenſure: The more part (from which moſt uſually ariſeth the denomination) were ſtill Saints; ſtill, his beloved ſons, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.14. ſtill, Brethren, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.11. the Apoſtle had reſpect unto Gods teſtimony, <hi>Act.</hi> 18.11. who aſſured him, that he had much people, in Corinth.</p>
            <p>Know moreover, ſaith<note n="t" place="margin">Pet. Martyr, loc. com. claſſ. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi> Sect. <hi>1.</hi> &amp; p. ib. <hi>74<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Eccleſiam, non tollunt diſſidia</note> 
               <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> judiciouſly, <hi>Non ob quamcunque maculam Christi Eccleſiam ità exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere, ut Dei non ampliùs appelletur;</hi> Every little blemiſh, in the face of a Church, cannot cut off a Church from being Gods; no more, than a man moleſted by an ulcer, or a ſore, doth ceaſe, for [that] alone, to be a man: in S. <hi>Gregory Nazianzen</hi> dayes, their were 600 errors, in the Church; do theſe, any wayes, derogate from the truth, and worth of Chriſtian Religion? The Church, <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.10 is reſembled to the Moon, which, ye know, when tis moſt radiant, and full of luſtre, ſhines but in a borrowed light; and ſtill, ſome blots remain indeleble therein, even incapable of any illumination; the coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt veſture may take a rent; which rent may be repair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:124195:12"/>without the utter abjection of the garment even as ſome one tile, or more, miſplaced, or ſhaken, or grown looſe, in the houſe-top, muſt not forth with occaſion the taking down of the whole roof, or contignation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Neque vero <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> eſt Eccleſia Dei, que infuſcari labe aliquâ non poſſit, aut non interd<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m egeat inſtanratione;</hi> as that<note n="u" place="margin">Juel. Apol. p. <hi>95.</hi> vol. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Jewel</hi> of his time, (a Prelate of immortall memory) ſaith divinely: why are the Apoſtles, and their ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, ſtiled<note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 10.12.</note> Shepherds, and<note n="*" place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt. 3.3.</note> Watchmen, and<note n="*" place="margin">Matth. 9.12.</note> Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians if there are no ſheep apt to<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.25.</note> ſtraggle, and need recalling; if no woolfe, to worrie the flock; no lambe, that aileth ought, or needs an healing; Beleeve it, my beloved Chriſtians, the Church militant here belowe, on earth, ſhall never be without ſome wrinkles of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections, and ſpots of infirmity; till ſhe becomes compleatly, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a glorious Church triumphant, above in heaven, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.27. <hi>Coelum ipſum nulla ſerenitas tàm celatu purgut, ut hon alicujus nubeculae flocculo reſigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> as<note n="w" place="margin">Tertul. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi> contr. Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones.</note> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> elegantly; in the cleareſt ſerenitie of the firmament, ſome ſpecking cloud may be diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; as that mole was, in the very face of <hi>Venus;</hi> or a foil nigh ſet to ſome precious Diamond.</p>
            <p>Thoſe <hi>Begardi,</hi> and <hi>Beguina,</hi> in <hi>Alemania,</hi> are juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, therefore, by<note n="x" place="margin">Alphonſus â Caſtro, adver. Haereſ. li. <hi>3.</hi> fol. <hi>217.</hi> E.</note> 
               <hi>Alphonſus â Caſtro,</hi> condemned, as idle dreamers, and Heretiques, who aſſerted apoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of an abſolute perfection of Beatitude, atteinable, even in this life; whereas, indeed, faith the devout S.<note n="y" place="margin">Multum in hâc vitâ ille profecit, qui, quàm longè ſit â perfectione juſtitiae, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiendo cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit, S. Auguſt. de ſpir. &amp; lit. c. <hi>36.</hi>—con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer. Fulgent. l. <hi>1.</hi> ad Moni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum, p. <hi>20.</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Auſtin,</hi> the beſt Chriſtians perfection conſiſts alone in this; to ſee, and to acknowledge his<note n="z" place="margin">Vide Joh. Voſſium, theſ. Theolog. De bonis oſeribus, p. <hi>60. 61.</hi> &amp;c. it. ib. p. <hi>564. 565.</hi> theſ. <hi>7.</hi> &amp; p <hi>579. 580</hi> theſ. <hi>12.</hi> de virtu<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gentil.— <hi>See</hi> Arr. <hi>26. of the Church of England:</hi> Confer Bp. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher. c. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>20.</hi> &amp;c. 7. p. <hi>66. of the Iriſh Reſig.</hi> &amp; D. Field, l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. <hi>16.18. of the Church, &amp; Bp.</hi> Hall, <hi>holy obſer. 88</hi> l. <hi>1.</hi> &amp; D. Rainolds, concluſ. <hi>5. againſt</hi> quaeſt. <hi>1.</hi> p. <hi>5. 6. 7.</hi> &amp; qu. <hi>8.</hi> p. <hi>43</hi> &amp; qu. <hi>29.</hi> p. <hi>132.</hi> edit. Cantab. Ann. <hi>1634.</hi> &amp; Mr. Reynolds, Medit. <hi>on the Lords Supper,</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>7. 12. 13. 14. and infinite others.</hi>
               </note> imperfection; or, in S.<note n="a" place="margin">S. Bern. Epiſt. <hi>253.</hi> fol. <hi>262.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bernards</hi> expreſſion, <hi>Indefeſſum proficiondi ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, &amp; jugis c<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tus ad perfectionem, perfectio reputatur;</hi> An unwearied<note n="b" place="margin">N<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. 1.11.</note> deſire of, and conſtant<note n="c" place="margin">Phil. 3.14.</note> endeavour after perfection, is, <hi>interpretative,</hi> in Gods eſteeme, perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:124195:12"/>it ſelf: And indeed, what Saint is he, who ſhall not be forced, often, to acknowledge; that, when he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours moſt to faſten his cogitations upon God, he findeth not his minde unſteadie; and to be, even as when we look upon a ſtarre (as one compates it) through an optique glaſſe, with a palſey-ſhaking hand; its long, c're we can bring our minds, to have ken of him &amp; to place our eyes upon him; and when we have come to that; how do our hands ſhake, and ſoon looſe the ſight again or, if ye will, it fareth with the minde, in this, as it doth with one, that windeth up an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; that, as often the pegs<note n="d" place="margin">Qui non ſentit malae concupiſcentiae [Renitentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>] in honis ſuis actionibus, hune ego nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>law bona<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem unquam feciſſe ſentio<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Bp.</hi> Davenant <hi>of Salisbury,</hi> quaeſt. <hi>10.</hi> p. <hi>52.</hi> qua ſupra.</note> ſlip between our fingers, whileſt we are in winding of them up; ſo do our verie beſt thoughts, whileſt they are in raiſing up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, unto a contemplation of heaven.</p>
            <p>Surely, men even the holieſt, whileſt they live [in] the fleſh, have ſome<note n="e" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Rainolds</hi> againſt <hi>Hart,</hi> c. 1. <hi>diviſ.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 9.</note> contagion, [of] the fleſh: ſin, that<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 7.24.</note> body of death, as a Jebuſite in Canaan, will not out, univerſally, of the coaſts of our natures, till the death of the body: wherefore, that ſame<note n="g" place="margin">Vide <hi>Biſhop</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher, Primar. Armachan. p. <hi>225 226. &amp;c.</hi> de Britan, Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. Primord.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and that ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Impaſſibilitie, and, as S. <hi>Hierome</hi> renders it, impeccancie; were the <hi>Dalilah's</hi> of that damned Heretique <hi>Pelagius,</hi> long ſince, juſtly exploded from all Chriſtian, and modeſt cares: it is with the primeſt Saint upon earth, in reſpect of grace, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, as with an inſtrument ſtrung with two ſtrings; the one made of the gut of a lambe; the other, of a woolf, <hi>fidibus lupi male obſtrepunt agninae,</hi> ſaithwitty <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan;</hi> the one makes an harſh jarring againſt the other.</p>
            <p>Even thoſe very Cedars of the Church received, once, a ſhock; <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> I mean, (whom yet the <hi>Lyſtrians,</hi> for the admirable graces ſo reſplendent in them, thought to have been<note n="h" place="margin">Act. 14.11.</note> Gods come down from heaven, in the ſimilitude of men) even thoſe great A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles jarred; and had, ſometime, moſt ſharp [con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions] among themſelves, <hi>Act.</hi> 15.39. yea, even S. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf, that rock for his faith, was yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, as worthy of blame, to the very face, by the ſame Apoſtle, <hi>Galat.</hi> 2.11.<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:124195:13"/>
            <p>Truly made king <hi>Solomon</hi> the compariſon of the Church, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.2. to a lilly among [thorns]; if ſhe be a lilly, lovely to look upon, by the eyes of her myſtical Husband Chriſt; yet, living, or ſeated among [thoms], ſhe may be torn, and rent into a Schiſme: It was no wonder then, that here, among the very [Saints] in Corinth, (chiefly, when, as yet, but [weak] in faith, and [babes] in Chriſt, not totally uncarnalized, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3.) there aroſe diviſions.</p>
            <p>And yet, thoſe private Schiſmes, in a [few], could not diſchurch the Citie of [all] the Saints; for howbeit, there were diviſions among [ſome] of them; yet were they ſtill, [for the main body of them] a deare, and ſolid Church of God. And thus much of the explication of my ſecond par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular; namely, the place, where; or, if ye will, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, among whom, diviſions did ariſe; even in, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the [Church] of Corinth; For, ſo is the Text; <hi>Firſt of all, when ye come together, in the [Church], I hear, that there are diviſions among you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Follows next the mean,<note place="margin">The 3. part.</note> whereby the Apoſtle came to know there were diviſions among them; it was by Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I hear ſo: And withall, the meaſure of his credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, upon that hereſie; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I [partly] beleeve it: both of theſe I ſhall fold up, in a compendious diſcourſe together; that I may haſten unto that, which is the life of a Sermon; the Application of this firſt Generall.</p>
            <p>And firſt of the mean of his information, Hear ſay; <hi> [hear], there are diviſions among you:</hi> We ſee here, how the Pilote, that now ſteered the Apoſtle unto this charge of Schiſme, upon Corinth, was an holy prudence, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion; he made not his own brain the mint, wherein to coine ſo high a taxation; nor his heart the ſhop, in which to forge it; but, he took it upon [report], and, as<note n="i" place="margin">Eſtius, ad <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>1.11.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Estius</hi> wel obſerves; leſt they might ſurmiſe, he was ſome zealous Camelion, to feed his credulity, onely on the aire of rumor, or of uncertain bruits, at large; he names the houſhold of <hi>Cloe,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.11. a Chriſtian, and a godly Matron, in the Citie, not more eximious for devotion, than fidelity; as if, what S. <hi>John</hi> adviſed of ſpirits, S. <hi>Paul</hi> obſerved in fames; he would not<note n="k" place="margin">1 Ioh. 4.1.</note> beleeve everie report; but try them firſt, whether they were of truth, or not.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:124195:13"/>
            <p>And when he had done thus;<note place="margin">The 4. part.</note> he would not neither be a ſponge, to ſuck in all without a difference; and ſo to ſponge with vinegar, and gall, or, to ſhoot out the arrows of bitter words, and of a virulent invective againſt them all; but lo! he carried a Chancery within his own breaſt, to mitigate the rigour of common hearſay, with equall candor, and favourable interpretations; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he did but part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeve it.</p>
            <p>Which practiſe of the Apoſtle ſhould be the mould for all moderate, and wiſe Chriſtians,<note place="margin">Rules to direct cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, in the point of Reports.</note> to caſt the order of their own credulity (for matter of criminall imputation) in, to as that charity be not impeached.</p>
            <p>The Rules are theſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule </seg>1</label> Firſt, Charitable credulity is not grounded on ſurmiſes cauſeleſſe, not is it ſuſpitious in vain; 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. Charity thinks not evill; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it deviſeth not evill, is not the firſt projector, or contriver of it: unlike to thoſe vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Enginers, <hi>Jer.</hi> 20.10. who, by an ungodly arietation, [deviſed] how to batter the reputation of the holy Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and to lay the honour of his good name, in duſt, and ruine; Report, ſay they, &amp; we will report it; peradventure, he will be entiſed and we (though by our very lies) may yet prevail againſt him; yea, take our full revenge upon him: Lord! what cruell murtherers were theſe, thus to ſtab the holy Prophet abſent? allowing him no life, without the death of his good name; in the mean time, never ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomizing, or opening their own ulcerous inſides; or, ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with thoſe ſouldiers, <hi>Luk.</hi> 3 14. And what ſhall [we] do? but, as thoſe Grecians, in<note n="*" place="margin">Suidas.</note> 
               <hi>Suidas,</hi> who were wont to write, whether with ink, or blood, on a glaſſe, and ſo to ſet it againſt the Moon, when t'was at full and brighteſt; and ſo thoſe ſpots, that were in the glaſſe, they would make to be in the Moon; In like ſort, do ſome envious perſons, (ſuch, as, in the expreſſion of<note n="l" place="margin">Theophr. in Charac.</note> 
               <hi>Theophraſtus,</hi> labour of a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which the learned <hi>Caſaubon</hi> renders by, <hi>Famigera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores,</hi> or, as<note n="m" place="margin">Plautus in Trinum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo.</note> 
               <hi>Plantus,</hi> are <hi>goruli figuli</hi>) they make thoſe blurs, which paſſion, or diſcontent, (both of which, often, either utterly break the bars, or lift the doore of reaſon off the hinges) occaſion, to be in him, who is maligned; ſuch are not much unlike that Theban <hi>Crates,</hi> in <hi>Laertius,</hi> who
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:124195:14"/>was nicknamed, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a doore-opener, becauſe he uſed to ruſh into every other mans houſe, and there to find our faults; but like thoſe hags, or fairies, (called <hi>Lamiae</hi>) though they ſaw well abroad, and can ask, as S. <hi>Peter</hi> once did cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly about S. <hi>John,</hi> 21.21. And, what ſhal [this] man do? yet they put up their eyes in boxes, when they come at home; becoming like <hi>Calisto,</hi> in the Poet, who being me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamorphoſed, by <hi>Juno,</hi> into a Beare; yet could ſhe never perceive, or ſee her own deformitie: This makes ſo many prodigall, and laviſh of their neighbours reputation, and to hang up their good names, as it were, in chains at their own doores: whereas, indeed, good name is, and ought to be as dear to all good men, as is the precious life it ſelf; <hi>Qui fidens Conſcientiae ſuae negligit famem ſuam, crudelis eſt,</hi> as S.<note n="n" place="margin">S. Auſt. de diverſ. Ser. <hi>49.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſweetly; He is, after a ſort, an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as I may ſtile him, <hi>à ſui-Timon,</hi> a ſelf-man-hater; who ſo far leaneth on the ſtaffe of his good conſcience [within] him, that he neglects the bulwark of his good name [without] him: <hi>Propter nos, conſcientia noſtra ſufficit nobis, propter vos, fama noſtra non pollui, ſed pollexe debet in vobis,</hi> ſaith the ſame Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; A clean conſcience, indeed, may, as that coſtly ſpike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard of <hi>Mary Magdalene,</hi> Joh. 12.3. ſill, with its fragrant odour, the whole houſe of the ſoul [within] doores; but, beleeve it, brethren, the good<note n="o" place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Sclater,</hi> on 1 Theſ. <hi>p.</hi> 156. 157. — <hi>&amp; p.</hi> 305.— 551. 552. <hi>confer Mr. Edw. Reinolds,</hi> on Pſal. 110. <hi>p.</hi> 475. 476.</note> name is that, which, as King <hi>Solomons</hi> ointment, <hi>Can.</hi> 1.3. (far more precious, than the gold of Ophir) is poured forth abroad, perfuming with its good ſavour, all ſuch as are [without] us, or that wiſh us well: wherefore, our Apoſtle here, as, he endeavoured to have <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, an inoffenſive conſcience toward [God], <hi>Act.</hi> 24 16. ſo withall, he ſtudied to provide things honeſt, and of good report, before all [men] too, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.17. and <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8. And, for this cauſe, he would not [create] a ſcandall on the Church of Corinth; but entertained the noiſe of a ſchiſme in it, on a fair report; ſo is the Text, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>I [hear], that there are diviſions among you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule </seg>2</label> A ſecond Rule is this; that, as our credulity muſt be grounded on a creditable report, or fame; ſo, becauſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, often, takes a bluſh of ſome particular intereſt, or affection from him, who makes it; the probabilitie of the [thing] it ſelf muſt next be heeded; ſo here, its [likely]
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:124195:14"/>that there ſhould be ſchiſms, for there [muſt] be hereſies: Its a moſt ſatanicall evil, maliciouſly to deviſe [impoſſible] things, that thou mighteſt accuſe thy brother.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Rule </seg>3</label> To this there ſhould be added [evidence], to evince what is reported, as here, <hi>ver.</hi> 20, 21. their ſchiſme [appeared] openly, through too great ſiding, and contempt of weaker brethren.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, becauſe, in never ſo manifeſt facts; there may be, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, ſome circumſtances of extenuation; its a ſafe way, ſtill to hope the beſt, and rather to chuſo, to beleeve too little, than too much, for, where too much charity hath, as <hi>Saul,</hi> ſlain its thouſands; too little hath, as <hi>David,</hi> ſlain its ten thouſands.</p>
            <p>An exhortation, in this age of ours, (I had almoſt ſaid alſo, in this Metropolis of ours) moſt opportune, and ſeaſonable: For were it to be wiſhed, that we could more tenderly, and with this Apoſtolicall prudence, handle the reputation of our brethren; chiefly of [Miniſters]; for, of all the horrible offences, that bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ruine, and deſolation to that City of God, Jeruſalem; this one alone is mentioned, as the modell, and the ſum of all, (after which, deſtruction was inevitable) namely, the abuſing, and the killing, and the ſtoning of Gods Meſſengers, and of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, that were ſent unto them, for to ſave their ſouls; when once thoſe holy inſtruments of their converſion became con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible, and an ungracious by word; behold! then, there was no more Remedie; Jeruſalem's houſe is left unto her deſolate, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.37. compare 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 36.16. but yet, with greater ſpecialty, beware we, how we ſlander [whole] Churches, and the governours thereof, without diſtinction; S. <hi>Paul's</hi> aſperſion was but onely of ſome [few] particulars, in Corinth; the main [body] of them was ſtill unblemiſhed.</p>
            <p>And yet, who ſees not, now too many, (but, the beſt is, ſtore of thoſe many are but like to looſe teeth, in a mans head, though troubleſome, yet uſeleſſe) how do they, by the purulent excreations of their corrupt lungs, (found upon their libellous, abuſive, and irreligious pamphlets; by which, as that Fly, in the lable, upon the axle-tree; they phanſie that they have raiſed up a mighty duſt, and made a ſmother) odiouſly beſpawle the beautious face of our deare Mother, the Church of England; whoſe two breaſts (the two bleſſed Teſtaments) ſhe being farre more uberous, and free of her duggs, (then was that <hi>Iſis mammoſa</hi> of the Egyptians) offer themſelves, ſo freely, to be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:124195:15"/>joyntly ſucked by us all.</p>
            <p>What one point is there of her Doctrine, or of her Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline, which ſhe maintaineth; I ſay not, what this, or that particular man [inventeth] but, what ſhe, her ſelf, [maintaineth]; that hath not been confirmed, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſprinkled, &amp; even enamelled with the very precious pearls of the bloud of the bleſſed Saints, (our own dear Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treymen and Forefathers) as ever held up innocent hands to God?</p>
            <p>Let not, oh let not that pearl of prejudice be [ever], in the eye of any your judgements, or miſ-conceit; ſo that, rather for defect of will, then otherwiſe, yee cannot view the decency, and order which (as ſweet, &amp; goodly flowers, hung in the Chaplet of Reformation) do ſo much grace, and beautifie a Church. S.<note n="p" place="margin">S. Augu. Epiſt. <hi>i 91.</hi> confer Bp Juel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Harding, p. <hi>291. 292.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſtin,</hi> I acknowledge, once complained, that the Church, in his daies, was burthened by too many ceremonies; and therefore he, as an Evange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall <hi>Aholiab,</hi> or <hi>Bezaleel,</hi> thought meet, to lay [by] ſome what of that <hi>nimium,</hi> or<note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 36.5.</note> [too-much] of what was offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, by the ſons, to adde unto the glory of the mother; and, in his ſenſe, a ſtatute of Mortmain might have been uſeful: But ſure, he had no ſacrilegious thought, at that time, then; nor I preſume, any true ſon of the Church of God, at this day, now; under a pretenſe to cure a Timpany of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluities, to cut off the fleſh of the Churches maintenance: we have better, I truſt, learned to know, and to fear too, that heavy, preſaged doom of<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>See Bp</hi> Andrews, <hi>his</hi> Concio ad Cleru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, pro gradu Doctor<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, inter ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ſua <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> poſt huma, in fronte, <hi>on Prov. 20.25.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 20.25. It is a [ſnare] to any man, to devoure that which is holy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne not then a [whole] Church, for the error, or, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, the ſuperſtitions of a [few]. But ſurely, it is too true; we are ſtill too-credulous, on the worſer part; and, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of ſpight, or pride, or ſelf-love, or all, or worſe, (I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell), by a ſinfull Chymiſtry, we labour to extract our own, out of the ruin of anothers ſame: And bence come thoſe uncharitable, and, moſt times, fond ſurmizes, which make men gaſh deep wounds, on the [intentions], when to the outward [actions], as good, at laſt indifferent; their cenſures ſhall be forced to ſtoop, as the ſheaves of <hi>Joſephs</hi> brethren bowed to the ſheaves of <hi>Joſeph.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:124195:15"/>
            <p>To end this point, let us all therefore conſider, how precious a thing good name is; farre more, than gold, or rubies, yea, or the coſtlieſt ointment, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.1. And if that bee true (as 'tis moſt certaine,) that Treſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes againſt [men,] receive their greatneſſe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the [dammage,] brought thereby unto them; ſure it is, wee ſin more hainouſly, in abuſing [fame,] than wee can doe poſſibly, by impeaching any other of their outward [goods;] for, after that old Rule, <hi>non dimittitur p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ccatum, niſi reſtituatur ablatum;</hi> its much more poſſible and facile, to [reſtore] letriments in [goods,] than blemiſhes brought to the [fame] of our brethren; yea or of a Church: 'Twas <hi>Machia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill's</hi> plot, <hi>audacter calumniare, &amp; aliquid haereſcit;</hi> and uſually, they find (chiefely in great crimes) a wound, and diſhonour, ſuch as is never done away.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, in all ill reports, offered to our eares, let us ſtil place, neare by our overhaſty, and prepro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous credulity, a temper of equall Candor and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity: the braine is the coldeſt part in man, and is ſo placed, ſay Phyſitians, to allay the heat of the liver; which being the fountaine of bloud and ſpirits, would elſe ſet the whole body in a combuſtion; ſo ſhould our moderation herein, by a Chriſtian <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, allay our temerity; and like the water, obſerved by Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomiſts, in the pericardium, coole the ebullitions about the heart; or even as the Chryſtalline Sphaere (by which ſome thinke, meant thoſe waters [above] the firmament, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.7) is placed next to the <hi>primum mobile,</hi> to allay the extremity of heat, raiſed by ſo vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent a motion, as would without a temper, fire the Vniverſe, and in a moment, waſt the World into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes: Caſting (as I ſaid but now) our practiſe in this, in the mould of the Divine Apoſtle; who, when ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings were brought him in of ſome Diviſions in <hi>Corinth,</hi> would not ſuffer his beliefe to over-reach; he did but [partly] credite the report; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:124195:16"/>ſo is the Text, I [heare,] that there are Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions among you, and I [partly] beleeve it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>
               </label> And thus have I gone over all the foure parts of this verſe, which were as the ſeverall pictures hung about the firſt roome; the doore into which the key of my Diviſion unlocked.</p>
            <p>Now if I were as happy, as <hi>Solomon</hi> was, that I might have whatſoever I would aske; I would at this time begge this favour of God, <hi>viz.</hi> that every particular hearer, within this audience, this day, might throughly reſolve in conſtancy, what the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> once did in a fit, upon an earneſt admonition from <hi>Joſhua,</hi> 1.16. All that is now by God commanded them they would doe; and become as ſo many ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and Divine <hi>Proteûs,</hi> to <hi>Metamorphoſe</hi> theſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions into a zealous, and conſcientious practiſe: And indeed, the very mention of my doubts herein, had need crave pardon of preſumption from all [good] hearts; for [ſuch,] (as Saint<note n="r" place="margin">S. Auguſt. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. <hi>252.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> courted ſome on another occaſion) I have but ſhewen them a mirrour of what they are, and ſhould but waſt my breath, to inſtruct them further unto what they ſhould bee: All the oile, that I ſhall further powre into ſuch blazing Lamps of piety, is onely, in the expreſſion of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> to his <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> a petition; that they would<note n="ſ" place="margin">1 <hi>Theſſal.</hi> 4 10.</note> encreaſe more and more.</p>
            <p>But, as there is no Pomegranate, wherein ſome graines are not rotten; ſo few aſſemblies where ſome are not, either, as the Apoſtles auditours at <hi>Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, Act.</hi> 2.13. Mockers; or as Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> hearers at <hi>Athens, Act.</hi> 17.18. that in a Stoicall or an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curean flout, eſteeme the Preacher but a Babler; or as thoſe that liſtened to our Saviours Sermons, to [catch] him in his diſcourſe, <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.15. or at beſt, unfruitfull in all holy practiſe; ſo it may bee, ſome ſuch may have borrowed a vizar; and like thoſe in the<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.31.</note> Prophet, <hi>Come hither and fit before the Lord as his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple;</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:124195:16"/>whereas yet, their hearts are lodged (and it grives mee to ſay it,) as thoſe <hi>Philiſtims</hi> ſmitten before <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 14.11. in <hi>Baal-perazim,</hi> even in the valley of Diviſions.</p>
            <p>What elſe meaneth this<note n="u" place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.14.</note> bleating of the ſheepe, and this lowing of the oxen in our eares? ſuch a noiſe of diſſenſions in the Church, for which as of old, for the<note n="w" place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 5, 15.</note> diviſions of <hi>Reuben,</hi> there are great thoughts of heart: A theame better ſuting with our teares, that wee cannot reforme them; than with our lips, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime againſt them: And woe is mee for my mother, my<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lam.</hi> 1.20.</note> bowels, my bowels! that what thoſe did once in <hi>Babylon,</hi> in a<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 137.4.</note> ſtrange Land; the quiet and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſons of the Church, ſhould now bee occaſioned to doe at home in their owne Land; even to hang up their harpes upon the willowes, when they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thee ô <hi>Syon!</hi> For, whereas wee are exhorted to keepe the<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 41 3.</note> Vnity of the Spirit, in the bond of peace, loe! as if with thoſe <hi>Antitactae</hi> of old, wee meant to contradict the Goſpell; what is there almoſt but ſtrife, and contention in the Church? witneſſe the miſerable diſtraction of the Chriſtian World, in point of Religion; which for the ſinnes of the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, (whoſe<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 76.10.</note> fierceneſſe, notwithſtanding, the Lord ſhall at length turne unto his owne praiſe and glory.) Seemes to have received ſo wide wounds in the ſides thereof, that none but Heavens Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giry can cure: And indeed, it often ſo fals out, as the Cardinall<note n="b" place="margin">Cardinalis Perona, in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. ad Regem Franciae. p. <hi>142. 145.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Per<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one</hi> adviſed the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> in the caſe of the <hi>Venetian</hi> ſtirre, about the <hi>Ieſuites;</hi> (it was at that time, when hee told his holineſſe plainely, that the State ſtood ſo;) and every day more and more may it be ſo ſtill!) that hee muſt now be forced to court the favour of Chriſtian Princes; and not, as formerly Chriſtian Princes ſue to him; Hee told his holineſſe then, that <hi>Saepè providentiâ divinâ permitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ut etiàm [juſtae] cauſae vim patiantur, propter pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:124195:17"/>populorum;</hi> By Divine providence, it was often permitted, that even [juſt] cauſes ſuffer much for the ſinnes of the people.</p>
            <p>O Religion, Religion! It is a word derived, ſaith<note n="c" place="margin">Lactant. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>28.29.</hi> De vera Sap. <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer</hi> Calvin. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi> Sect. <hi>1.</hi> inſtit. &amp; Epiſc. Daven. quaeſt. <hi>12</hi> quâ ſuprâ, ex S. Auguſt. l. <hi>10</hi> de Civ. c. <hi>1. A<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d Bp.</hi> King <hi>explaining it,</hi> Lect. <hi>16. on</hi> Jonah, p <hi>204. 205</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Lactantius, à religando,</hi> from uniting, and knitting Chriſtians together, in one indiſſoluble, and firme bond: but, behold! how diſtractions in religions are like to bee, (without a ſeaſonable prevention) the deſtruction of Religion; and Religion it ſelfe to bee, in a manner, loſt in the quarrels, and queſtions of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</p>
            <p>If, after ſubſtance, yee recount Religions, there have beene in the World, from the firſt foundation thereof, (ſaith that incomparable<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hooker, l.</hi> 5. <hi>p.</hi> 367. Confer D. <hi>Field, l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. Of the Church.</note> Writer of the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Polity) but onely three.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Paganiſme,</hi> which lived in the blindneſſe of corrupt, and depraved nature.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Iudaiſme</hi> embracing the Law, which reformed Heatheniſh impiety, and taught ſalvation to bee expected through a <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> that ſhould in due time, come into the World.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Chriſtian</hi> beliefe, which yeildeth obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to the Goſpell of IESUS CHRIST, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth him alone, to bee the Saviour, whom God did promiſe.</p>
            <p>But, if yee number Religions, after opinion; then wee have<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bp.</hi> Hall, Dec. <hi>3.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>3—Conf.</hi> Burton, Melanch, part. <hi>3.</hi> Sect. <hi>4.</hi> p. <hi>513</hi> &amp;c.</note> five at leaſt: 1. <hi>Iewiſh.</hi> 2. <hi>Turkiſh.</hi> 3. <hi>Greekiſh.</hi> 4. <hi>Popiſh.</hi> 5. <hi>Reformed.</hi> And<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Fuller, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>Hiſt.</hi> of the Holy Warre.</note> 
               <hi>Poland</hi> is the <hi>Pantheon</hi> of all Religions; and <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> the patterne of all Sects; and woe is mee! that even [it] ſhould now ſeeme to bee let looſe on [us:] In at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempting to ſpeake of theſe; ſhall I ſmile with <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mocritus?</hi> or weepe with <hi>Heraclitus?</hi> they are ſo ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous, and abſurd on the one ſide; ſo lamentable, and tragicall, on the other: But, what is to be thought, when about the perſwaſions in one, and the ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; wee ſhall heare the meere language of <hi>Babel,</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:124195:17"/>when the tongues were divided and<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 11.7.</note> confounded? I am of <hi>Luther,</hi> ſaith one; I of <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaith a ſecond; I of <hi>Arminius</hi> a third; I of <hi>Fraucis,</hi> I of <hi>Dominick,</hi> I of <hi>Ieſus;</hi> and in this jangling, none almoſt for <hi>Chriſt:</hi> it faring with Religion, ſaith a Reverend<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>D</hi> Curle, <hi>now Bp. of</hi> Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter, Ser. <hi>on</hi> Hebr. <hi>12.14.</hi> Edit. An. <hi>162 2.</hi>
               </note> Prelate, as it did with her, in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> who had many Sui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours; when every one could not have her to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, they pulled her all in pieces, that ſo none might have her; for ſo many in Religion, <hi>Malunt nullam habere, quàm non ſuam:</hi> They had rather there ſhould bee none at all, than that their owne ſhould not take place; yea, in ſuch bitterneſſe of Spirit, are the ſons of the ſame Church carried; that one in a manner, is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a curſe, and execration to another; blowing the Trumpet of<note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.1</note> 
               <hi>Sheba,</hi> in a mutuall defiance, and ſaying: <hi>They have no part in God, nor in the inheritance of his Son</hi> CHRIST IRSUS; <hi>every man to his Tents, ô Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Lord! my deare brethren, what can Religion, ſo<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 3.24.</note> divided againſt it ſelfe, portend, or bode, but over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw, and ruine? 'Twas a rule in <hi>Matchiavel, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide &amp; impera:</hi> The mind of man is like the ſtone <hi>Tyrrhenus;</hi> that ſtone, ſolong as it is whole, like to the miraculous yron of <hi>Eliſha,</hi> [<note n="i" place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 6.6.</note> ſwimmeth;] but, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing once broken, loe! as that lead of <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 15.10. it [<note n="k" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Plaif.</hi>
               </note> ſinketh] in the mighty waters: what ſo neare one, as two? and yet wee muſt not goe ſo farre from one, as two: The whole World ſaid <hi>Alexander,</hi> could not hold two Sunnes at once; nor ſurely, (with any happineſſe) one Church, [<note n="l" place="margin">See Bp. <hi>King. Lect.</hi> 7. on <hi>Jon. p.</hi> 98. 99. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> divided] Religions; no nor a [<note n="m" place="margin">See Dr. <hi>Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> my father, on 1. <hi>Theſſal c.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 6. and <hi>p.</hi> 426.</note> medly,] or a [mixture] of them at once.</p>
            <p>To draw to a concluſion of this part, Saint<note n="n" place="margin">S. Cyp. de unit. Eccl. Sect. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> ſaith, that our Saviour, <hi>Sacramento veſtis, &amp; ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no, declaravit Eccleſiae unitaetem;</hi> By his Coat, that was without<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joh.</hi> 19.23.</note> ſeame throughout, as by a ſigne declared; how his Church ſhould bee woven together in unity;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:124195:18"/>not piecen<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d up by that, which might bee rent into the ragges of Schiſme or Diviſions: Yet ſee and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, if this unſeamed Coat of his, bee not worſe dealt withall; than the Prophet <hi>Abijah,</hi> the Shilonite, did with that new garment, wherewith <hi>Ierobeam</hi> had clad himſelfe, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 11.30. Even rent into more than twelve pieces; as if the Body of the Lord CHRIST were no better, than the Body of that Harlot; which was chopt in pieces, fleſh, and bones, and all, and caſt into all the quarters of <hi>Iſrael, Iudg.</hi> 19.29.</p>
            <p>Leaſt I grow tedious, all that I ſhall adde, upon this point farther, ſhall bee epitomized under theſe two heads.</p>
            <p>Firſt, An Apotreptique, or Diſſwaſive from Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</p>
            <p>Secondly, A Protreptique, or Perſwaſive unto V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Love.</p>
            <p>For the firſt of theſe, though I might not [ſay,] but [thunder] with Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who aſſureth us, that ſuch as cauſe Diviſions in the Church, they ſerve not the Lord IESUS, <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.17.18. And againe, If any man love not the Lord IESUS CHRIST, let him be <hi>Anathema Maranatha,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.22. which ſhall hold likewiſe true of all ſuch, as doe not teſtifie their love to CHRIST, by their unfeigned love of their<note n="p" place="margin">1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.14.</note> brethren, his lively members; or as the ſame Apoſtle ſaid of ſome contentious <hi>Galatians,</hi> I would they were even<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.12.</note> cut off that trouble us: though thus I might doe; yet as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Philemon Verſe</hi> 9. For loves ſake, I rather beſeech them; and withall, I ſhall bee bold to tell them, that, where diſcords, and diviſions have gone before as <hi>Eſau;</hi> there ruines, and deſolations have beene wont to take them by the heele as <hi>Iacob:</hi> It hath beene found true in experience, that theſe have laid more Countries to the dition of the <hi>Turke,</hi> than ever his bow, and his ſhield could have
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:124195:18"/>purchaſed: It was prudently obſerved by <hi>Cortugall,</hi> one of the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Princes, in his oration perſwaſive to his Lord, to beſiege <hi>Rhodes; Chriſtianus occaſus diſcordi<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s inteſtinis corroboratur,</hi> The fall of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is ſet forward, by civill diſagrement: in the dayes of <hi>Mahomet</hi> the ſecond, thoſe polluted <hi>Sara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens,</hi> (to ſpeake in the expreſſion of a late<note n="*" place="margin">Bp. <hi>King.</hi>
               </note> worthy of our Church) had gleaned out of Chriſtendome, like ſcattered eares of corne, neglected by the owners,<note n="r" place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Jovium,</hi> and Dr. <hi>Helyn, Geograph.</hi> in deſcription of <hi>Rhodes.</hi>
               </note>200. Cities, 12. Kingdomes, and two Empires, what an earneſt they have reaped ſince that time, (or rather, wee reaped for them) who knoweth not? and yet, the Canker runneth on, fretting ſtill, and eating fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe the whole neglects the parts, and ſeeketh not to preſerve them: Beſides, who is not moved, till his very bowels are<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 11.8.</note> kindled together within him, to heare what muſique our <hi>Romiſh</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries have, too-long, made themſeves merry with in our diſcords? How long, Lord, holy and true? how long ſhall thoſe ſuperſtitious Maſſe and Merit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, (who dare obtrude their menſtruous me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits to thy dreadfull juſtice; and prophane the purity and ſimplicity of thy ſacred worſhip, by their gariſh vanities and Idolatry;) How long ſhall they triumph in our variance? O yee, that make a moſt unjuſt ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration on the other ſide, bee entreated, doe not thus give advantage to the Adverſary, by your cauſeles withdrawing of your ſelves from the Society of your Chriſtian brethren; who long for your uniformity, and joynt-adoration of the one onely true God; by the one, and onely Mediatour CHRIST IESUS; in one, and the ſame faith, once for all given to the Saints; in the uſe of one, and the ſame meanes of ſalvation; in the ſame Word, the ſame Sacraments, the ſame Miniſtery; in the unity of the ſame Spirit, that wee might all grow up together in the ſame love, and charity; and meete together at laſt, in one, and the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:124195:19"/>ſame Heaven: O ceaſe to eſteeme us, (your fellow-brethren in the ſame CHRIST,) who are of the ſame houſhold of faith with you; as<note n="*" place="margin">1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.20.</note> 
               <hi>Ahab</hi> did <hi>Elijah;</hi> or as the wavering, <hi>Galatians</hi> did Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> becauſe hee told them the truth, your [<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.16.</note> Enomies:] nor, as<note n="t" place="margin">Quae apud concordes, vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cula charitatis, incitamenta i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum, apud in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſos ſunt; <hi>Tacitus.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Tacitus</hi> ſaid of <hi>Segeſtes</hi> and <hi>Ariminius,</hi> the one, the father, the other, the Sonne in law: That which bound them together in love, whileſt they were at concord, put them farther at variance, being once enemies: Let a ſtreame ſever it ſelfe from the Common fountaine, that it may bee counted a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine it ſelfe, without dependance upon any other; what is this, but the next way, to make an end of it ſelfe, and to bee utterly dried up?</p>
            <p>Yea I beſeech you, conſider, when Noutrals, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts, and Prophane Perſons, and Papiſts, doe heare of ſo many diſcordant, and contrary opinions in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; doth it not harden them in their infidelity, avert them from the Church, and make them to ſit downe in the Chaire of Scornors? for it is certaine (as a great<note n="u" place="margin">My Lord <hi>Bacon, Eſſay.</hi> 3.</note> diſpenſer of learning obſerved, that Hereſies and Schiſmes, are of all others the greateſt ſcandals; yea more, than corruption of manners; for, as in the Naturall body, a wound, or ſolution of continuity, is worſt than a corrupt humour; ſo in the ſpirituall; ſo that nothing doth ſo much keepe men out of the Church, and drive men out of the Church as breach of Vnity: When Atheiſts looking on, ſhall view two Chriſtians [ſtriving] together, as: <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaw thoſe <hi>Iſraelites, Exod.</hi> 2.13. yea, ſo to bandy ignominious reproaches, each againſt the other, as if they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed but as a ſhepheard, and an <hi>Aegyptian;</hi> whereof the one ſaith <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> was an.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 46.34.</note> abomination to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; or like to that brood of <hi>Cadmus,</hi> of which the Poet,
<q>
                  <l>— Suo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </l>
                  <l>Marte ruunt ſubiti, per mutua vulnera fratres:</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:124195:19"/>or as it is obſerved of thoſe frighted <hi>Midianites, Iudg.</hi> 7.21. whoſe mutuall bowels became the ſheath of each others ſword: whereas indeed, each Chriſtian profeſſing one faith in one, and the ſame CHRIST, ſhould rather bee as thoſe <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> going up to <hi>Gibeah, Judg.</hi> 20.11. knit together as one man: can a Pagan otherwiſe imagine, that the CHRIST, wee all pretend to ſerve, is other, than what in truth the Lord abhorres to bee, even the Authour of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion? Loe! even briars, and thornes, the very Sonnes of <hi>Belial</hi> themſelves, are twiſted one within the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in a kind of indiſſoluble combination, or bond of Vnity: O my brethren, are there not ſtormes, and tempeſts enow abroad; raiſed up by <hi>Gebal,</hi> and <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> and <hi>Amalek,</hi> even by the boiſterous wild bores, and cruell adverſaries, to make the ſhip of the Church to reele, and ſtagger, and to bee driven upon the rocks; but the ſecret leakes of our owne home-variances muſt thus, inſenſibly, ſinke her, e're wee are aware? as if this ſhip were ſayling in a<note n="w" place="margin">Lacus inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, nullo flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te vento, it a im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſè concita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ut vel auda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſſimos nautas. quò minùs ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant, deterreat; undè, vento ceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſante, naves me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio curſucorreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae cum maximo diſcrimine je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantur, <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Geograph. pag. 46.</hi>
               </note> Loumond-lake (ſuch an one, as <hi>Maginus</hi> tels us, there is, in a part of <hi>Britaine,</hi>) in which, they ſay, the danger is then moſt formidable, when the winds are ſtill: To bee ſhort, Let us conſider, how bitter a word it was, that King <hi>David</hi> uttered of <hi>Joab,</hi> that, whereas the end of warre was peace, hee choſe to ſhed the bloud of<note n="x" place="margin">1 <hi>Kin.</hi> 2.5.</note> warre in peace, but, it coſt him deare at laſt: Now there is a ſaying in the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> that the Saints ſhall waſh their<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 58.10.</note> ſeete, in the bloud of the ungodly; to imply thus much, ſaith <hi>Lyra,</hi> that the righteous ſeeing the vengance, executed upon the ungodly for thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly deeds, they have committed, ſhall dread the like offences; leaſt they tread alſo in the like ſteps of judgement: are <hi>Halcyon</hi> dayes eſteemed happy? and peace, felicity? then, woe is mee, to thinke, that any man, or people ſhould waxe weary of their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe! is it not a very ſtrange infatuation? Its
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:124195:20"/>an old word, <hi>Quos Deus perdere vult, priùs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, I haſten to the other part, which is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treptique, or perſwaſive unto love, and unity: and, what ſtronger argument can there bee deviſed, to incline hereto; than this? that wee, hereby, come moſt neare unto the God, wee ſerve, and are even in this regard, partakers of the<note n="a" place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</note> Divine nature; though not, by communication of eſſence, yet by reſemblance, and analogicall aſſimilation, in that gracious quality: Hence was that Eulogy of <hi>Ephraim</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Ephraim. Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, tract. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Syrus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Happy is that man, who hath poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of love, for ſuch an one carrieth God alwayes with him, in his heart; for, ever ſo Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> aſſures us, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.16. <hi>God is love, and hee that dwelleth in love, dwelleth in God, and God in him:</hi> On the other ſide, ſaith<note n="c" place="margin">S. Ignatius, Epiſt. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ignatius,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Where there is diviſion of mind, and anger, and hatred, there God dwels not: Beſides, onely in love it is, that wee [reciprocate] with God, of all other affections; if wee feare God, hee feares not us; if wee obey God, hee obeyes not us; but, if wee love God, hee loveth us againe; 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.19. <hi>Love,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, it's the very<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Col.</hi> 3.14.</note> bond of perfection; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and who is able ſufficiently to amplifie the great things of the beauty of it? ſaith S.<note n="e" place="margin">S. Clemens, Epiſt. ad Corin. p. <hi>63. 64.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Clement,</hi> in his Epiſtle to theſe very <hi>Corith's;</hi> Sith it alone conglutinates us to God, and makes us alſo, to wiſh well to men: Vnity therefore is as another <hi>ordalium,</hi> to try the chaſtity of the Queene-Mother, the Church; and like a Gileaditiſh paſſage, at which the<note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 12.6.</note> liſping <hi>Ephraimites</hi> are diſcovered in their <hi>Sibboleth;</hi> at which the faultring Chriſtian will bee detected: For this cauſe, when the boſome favorites of CHRIST reſted in expectation of the holy Ghoſt promiſed, in a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:124195:20"/>miraculous manifeſtation, to bee ſent downe upon them, from heaven; they were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Act.</hi> 2.1. all together, in one place; and the ſame Spirit deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded before that, upon our Saviour himſelfe, in the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of a<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth</hi> 3.16.</note> dove; becauſe it is the uſuall embleme of<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Etymol.</note> love, and therefore, they who ſeparate, and breake this bond of love, are ſtyled ſenſuall, by Saint <hi>Iude, verſe</hi> 19. and without the<note n="g" place="margin">Tales itaque faciles ſunt ad diviſionem, quia Spiritum non habent, in quo uno membra Chriſti charam ſervant ſpirita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter unitatem, <hi>Fulgent.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> ad Monimum, p. <hi>67.</hi>
               </note> Spirit.</p>
            <p>Even the ſacred Trinity it ſelfe is delighted with the ſame Vnity, or One-neſſe, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.7. theſe three are one; there is but, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one God, and Father of all, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.6. but, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one Mediatour, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God, and Man, the Man CHRIST IESUS, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. There is but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one Spirit, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.11. All true-beleeving Chriſtians are but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one body, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.17. yea, but as one man, in CHRIST IESUS, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28.</p>
            <p>Even<note n="h" place="margin">Plato, lib. <hi>2.</hi> de Republ. ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus finem.</note> 
               <hi>Plato</hi> himſelfe would have children, by no means, to be told thoſe fictions of the Poets, touching the varience of the Heathen gods: In ſhort, there is no ſtable aſſurance of any other grace, in ſoundneſſe, ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from love: Faith indeed, is neceſſary, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t operis fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentum,</hi> as the foundation of charity, ſaith<note n="i" place="margin">Granatenſ. tom. <hi>3.</hi> conc. de temp. conc. <hi>1.</hi> in Die Pentecoſt.</note> 
               <hi>Granado;</hi> but charity, as the perfect conſummation of that gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Habite: hence was that maxime, in the Schoole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, that charity was the [forme] of all vertues Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall; becauſe, however it gave them not their owne eſſence, in themſelves, abſtractively conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; yet did it forme them unto [acceptability,] be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord: therefore, all other excellencies though they advance nature; yet they are, ſaith one, ſubject to [exceſſe,] onely this of charity admitteth no exceſſe; for, wee ſee, for aſpiring, to bee like God in [power,] the Angels tranſgreſſed, and fell; by aſpiring, to bee like God, in [knowledge,] man tranſgreſſed, and fell; but, by aſpiring to bee like God, in a ſimilitude of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:124195:21"/>goodneſſe, or [love;] neither man, nor Angell, ever tranſgreſſed, or ſhall tranſgreſſe; for, unto that imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wee are called: And, as its endles, in exceſſe; ſo alſo, in continuance, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.13.</p>
            <p>Now, according to the ſeverall motives, or grounds of love, ſo alſo is the [degree] ſeverall: There is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, when the motive, or ground is one, and the ſame nature; ſo ſaith the Philoſopher; if wee ſee a very Varlet in diſtreſſe; wee may, wee muſt relieve him; and give, though not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, yet <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, if not to the man, yet to the<note n="k" place="margin">Quantum ad ſuſtentationem [Naturae,] non ad ſomentum [culpae,] <hi>Tho. 2<hi rend="sup">a</hi>. 2<hi rend="sup">a</hi>.</hi> qu. <hi>31.</hi> Art. <hi>2.</hi> ad <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> nature; thus <hi>David,</hi> and his followers are ſaid to have relieved even a very <hi>Egyptian,</hi> when they found him languiſhing in the field, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30.11.12. and this love of nature, (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept directly to<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.31.</note> reprobates) is common unto all men; and very nature moved even <hi>Barbarians</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the diſtreſſed, <hi>Act.</hi> 28.2.</p>
            <p>Secondly, There is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a nearer bond; when vicinity, or cohabitation may induce to kindneſſe; and thus farre a meere Civilliſt may goe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; and this is onely the cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of true love Chriſtian; when wee love the brethren, <hi>Eo nomine,</hi> becauſe brethren, 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 3.14. and to this is that earneſt exhortation of Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.22. <hi>See that yee love one another with a pure heart fervently.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And I beſeech you brethren, in the bowels of our Common Saviour; let this intimation bee unto your hearts, as the Arteries running along the veines, which, beating upon them; ſtirre up the bloud, and keepe it warme, leaſt, otherwiſe, it ſhould congeale, and become as corall, and though wee cannot fly up, yet as the <hi>Cherubims,</hi> let us ſtill bee clapping of our wings, in our devotions, this way: And ſith, wee well accord, (I truſt) in the Principall<note n="m" place="margin">See Bp. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> his laſt booke.</note> fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall points of faith, for ſubſtance; let this ſeaſonable adviſe unto Vnity, bee, as the Angels ſnatching of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:124195:21"/>the ſword of <hi>Abraham,</hi> to ſtay the farther, and the future rending of our ſelves, into Schiſm's, and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions; in point of circumſtance, and of leſſer mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: Memorable is that ſtory of Saint <hi>Gregory Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zianzene,</hi> as<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ruffinns lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 9. <hi>Hiſt. Eccleſ</hi> —Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the ſtory of Bp. <hi>Colman,</hi> in Bp. <hi>Vſher, c.</hi> 10. of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Relig.-See Bp. <hi>Bilſon, c.</hi> 16. 395 <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Of the perpet, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church.</note> 
               <hi>Ruffinus,</hi> and others report it to us; who, in the tumults of the people cried out, <hi>Mitte nos in mare, &amp; non erit tempeſtas;</hi> That is, hee offered both his dignity, and himſelfe too: to bee caſt into the Sea, rather than the Vnity, and Peace of the Church ſhould ſuffer, or bee diſturbed: and indeed, what one true Sonne of the Church, who heartily longs for the<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.18.</note> building up, and delights not in the pulling downe of the walles of <hi>Hieruſalem;</hi> but would gladly bee content with <hi>Ionah,</hi> to bee caſt into the Sea, rather than the ſtorme ſhould continue, unto the endange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the whole ſhip?</p>
            <p>But, oh the deadneſſe of the heart, and the ſtoppage of the eares unto the voyce of the ſpirituall<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 58.5.</note> charmes, charme hee never ſo wiſely; for, though the bels of our Aarons have ſounded ſhrill; and every Pulpit, almoſt, (that hath any clapper,) tolled men long in, into the Temple of Peace; yet, if you aske them, as <hi>Iehoram's</hi> meſſenger did <hi>Iehu</hi> is it peace <hi>Iehu,</hi> they retort,<note n="q" place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 9.18.</note> what haſt thou to doe with peace? turne thee behind mee; alas! peace is not the matter, but follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and party: So true is that of<note n="r" place="margin">Salvian. l. <hi>4.</hi> ad Eccleſ. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thol. in fine.</note> 
               <hi>Salvian; Poenèom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis ſermo Divinus habet aemulos ſuos;</hi> almoſt every Precept of God meets with its adverſary; If God command liberality, Man will practiſe covetouſneſſe; if parſimony, prodigality; if hee ſpeake of<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 120.7.</note> peace, they make them ready for warre, as the Pſalmiſt hath it; impetuous <hi>Salamanders,</hi> who live not, but in the flames of contention; not unlike unto <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quinius Priſcus,</hi> in the <hi>Romane</hi> ſtory, who was<note n="t" place="margin">Luc. Florus, Hiſt.</note> 
               <hi>Bello promptior quàm pace;</hi> more apt in Warre, than peace; or, as <hi>Trogus</hi> tels us of the o<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>der <hi>Spaniards,</hi> that they were <hi>Genus hominum ità infenſum concordiae, ut puro
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:124195:22"/>illius odio, inimicitias ſuſcipiat:</hi> or, if men, that way af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, doe happily lend us their attentions; as the Iewes to <hi>Ieremy's</hi> paſſionate expreſſions; or, to <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiels</hi> pleaſant voyce<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.32.</note>; or, as <hi>Herod</hi> gave <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> the<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 6.20.</note> hearing, in ſome things; Yet, it cannot better bee reſembled, than by what is given us, in that fained relation of <hi>Orpheûs Theatre;</hi> where all birds, and beaſts aſſembled, and forgetting their ſeverall appetites; ſome of prey, ſome of game, ſome of quarrell, ſtood all ſociably together, liſtening unto the aires, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords of the harpe; the ſound whereof no ſooner ceaſed, or was drowned by ſome Lowder noiſe; but every beaſt returned to his owne Nature; ſo is the Nature, and Condition of men, (ſaith that emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent<note n="x" place="margin">Lo. <hi>Verul. l.</hi> 1. Advancem. of learning.</note> Patron of learning) who are full of ſavadge, and unreclaimable deſires, of profit, of luſt, of revenge; which, as long as they give care to Precepts, to lawes, to religion, ſweetly touched with eloquence, and perſwaſion of Sermons; ſo long is ſociety, and peace maintained; but, if theſe inſtruments bee ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, or that ſedition, and tumult make them not au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible; all things diſſolve into anarchy, and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>To conclude this whole application: Wee wiſh, that our words mght fall upon your hearts, as that Doctrine of <hi>Moſes, Deut.</hi> 32.2. dropped downe as the ſhowres of raine upon the graſſe, and our ſpeech might diſtill, as the dew, upon the tender herbe: or elſe, that your hearts might bee as the [water,] on which the Spirit of the Lord is ſaid to move, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.2. I ſay, on the [water,] not upon the [earth,] for hee will no muckiſh, earthy heart; nor moves hee on the [aire;] and heart ſwollen up with the wind of pride, and ambition; nor moves hee upon the [fire;] an heart enflamed with the ardor of choller, and concupiſcence; but, on the face of the [waters,] hearts, that are ſoft, and pliable to receive the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:124195:22"/>impreſſions of Gods grace: And, if not, as the graſſe, or the water, tender, and pliable; yet, at leaſt, as that rocke, in <hi>Ieremy,</hi> 23.29. which, though hard in it ſelfe, yet was it by the hammer of Gods word broken in pieces: but, oh the deadly perverſeneſſe of unſanctified ſoules! who, not onely as the ſame <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,</hi> 5.3. ſaith, of the obſtinate Iewes, have made their [faces] harder, than a rock; but, as it is ſaid of <hi>Nabal,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.37. Their very [hearts] are [dead] within them, and become as a ſtone; yea ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as <hi>Bonaventure,</hi> on like conſideration, inverted that prayer, in <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> 36.26. where God promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, to take away from them the heart of ſtone, and to give them an heart of fleſh; Nay rather, ſaith hee, take from us the heart of fleſh, and give us the heart of ſtone; for the ſtones, and the rockes were divided, and clave in ſunder, when our Saviour ſuffered, on the Croſſe; whereupon Saint <hi>Ambroſe, O ſaxis duriora Iudaeorum pectora!</hi> on ſuch ſtupid,<note n="y" place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.2.</note> ſeared conſciences, as theſe, I will not declaime; but convert a deſerved ſatyre into a mournefull elegy: my heart ſhall bleed, in ſecret, and mine eyes<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 119.136.</note> guſh out with teares, (thoſe ſpeechles Oratours of an unexpreſſable griefe) for that they will needs, like the waters of <hi>Iordan,</hi> ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by the mantle of <hi>Elijah,</hi> both bee, and remaine [<note n="*" place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 2.8.</note> divided:] <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith <hi>Sineſius:</hi> The ſincere, and entire Preacher, hath (in the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.4.</note> fruſtration of his hopes from his Hearers) no [other] at leaſt, no [ſuch] refuge to fly unto, at the laſt; but, as the Pigeons to their windowes, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.8. So hee, to his eyes; which are glazed with teares, (pearles farre more precious, than the waters, in thoſe wels of <hi>Elim,</hi> (to which the weeping Apoſtles are reſembled,) <hi>Num.</hi> 33.9.) when they are powred out for the ſinnes of the unreclaimable people: And ſuch as theſe, who ſo much hate to bee reformed, I leave to that heavy doome of our Saviour; upon the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:124195:23"/>Iewes on another occaſion, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 12.48. <hi>The word that I have now ſpoken, the ſame ſhall judge them, at the laſt Day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo taking my leave of theſe, with whom a pious diſcord is to bee choſen, and preferred, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an impious concord; (for, a juſt diſſenſion is much better, than an unjuſt peace; and ſuch an unjuſt peace is all peace, which is not, either joyned with, or elſe, (as ſome read that text) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, [according] to [holineſſe,] <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.14.) leaving theſe; I convert my ſelfe unto you,
<q>
                  <l>—Quibus arte benignâ,</l>
                  <l>Et meliore luto finxit pracordia Titan;</l>
               </q> Whoſe hearts the Lord hath moulded to an yeilding, and obedient conſtitution; fitted to receive the<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.30.</note> ſeale, and the marke of Gods Spirit: O bee you entreated, as our Saviour adviſed his owne deare Diſciples, Saint <hi>Marke</hi> 9.50. to have ſalt in your ſelves, and peace one with another; Now ſalt, as Saint<note n="a" place="margin">S. Hilar in S. Matth. can. <hi>4.</hi> Sal in ſe une continet ignis, &amp; aquae ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum, &amp; eſt reverâ unum ex duobus, h. e. Quid tertiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ex utro<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> coalitur, &amp;c. eſt aqua, ne plus ſatis inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcamus; eſt ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, ne tanquam frigore obterpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</note> 
               <hi>Hilary</hi> ſaith, containeth in its ſelfe the element both of fire, and water, and is indeed ſaith hee, a third thing, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted out of both; it is water; leaſt wee ſhould too-much bee incenſed unto heat, and paſſion; it is fire; leaſt wee ſhould grow too remiſſe, and chill, with neglect, and careleſneſſe: Firſt of all, have ſalt in your ſelves, that is, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> interprets, <hi>Col</hi> 4.6. Let your ſpeech bee alwayes with grace, ſeaſoned with falt; take heed, let it not bee rancid, or unſavoury, larded with bitter, and unchriſtian invectives; but tempered alwayes with ſobriety, meekeneſſe, and diſcretion: And then, when the ſalt is firſt ſet on upon the Table; peace, as the beſt, and choyceſt diſh, will follow after.</p>
            <p>Hence thoſe zealous exhortations of<note n="b" place="margin">S. Ignatius, Epiſt. ad Tral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian.</note> 
               <hi>Ignatius,</hi> and other Saints, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, love one another with an [undivided] heart; and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:124195:23"/>S. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.18. <hi>If it be poſſible, as much as ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in you, live peaceably with all men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is this enough, but we muſt follow after the [things] which [<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 14 19.</note> make] for peace; the word tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated here, [follow after], is in the originall [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] which ſignifieth, to purſue, and follow with eagernes of Spirit, even with as fervent an intention, as we have known ſome fierce, and violent perſecutor to follow-after the blood of an innocent Martyr; and who never reſteth ſatisfied, till hee hath even ſurfetted on his owne revenge: Now this eagernes fixed on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther object, may be imitated by us; even as our Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in this Text hath levelled it at the things, which make for peace.</p>
            <p>Now, what thoſe principall things are, that may,<note place="margin">What are the maine things that make for Peace.</note> indeed, be ſayd to make for Peace, the ſame Apoſtle hath epitomized into a ſhort compondium, in that one Text, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Now, J beſeech you, Brethren, by the name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> (ſaith he,) <hi>that yee all ſpeake the ſame thing, and that there be no diviſions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you; but that yee be perfectly joyned together, in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judgement:</hi> which words<note n="d" place="margin">Pet. Mart. loc. com. claſs. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> ſect. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> explicating, ſheweth us; that, as S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> juſtly maketh hatred againſt our neighbour, to be the maine cauſe of Schiſme; ſo, of that hatred, foure other principall cauſes may be given: 1. Firſt of all, that men accord not among themſelves, in regard of the firſt principles of faith; and therefore S. <hi>Paul,</hi> in this Text, deſires the Corinthians to be joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the ſame [mind]; that is, as I apprehend it; Whereas the mind is the principall faculty of the ſoule, and (as<note n="e" place="margin">Eſtius, ad <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>1.10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Eſtius</hi> criticizeth it) <hi>mens in cognitione ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetur,</hi> it is principally converſant in matter of Science, and Knowledge, therefore, the mind, and vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſhould be determined <hi>ad idem,</hi> and the object thereof, for the prevention of diviſions, ſhould be one and the ſame thing, for matter of the chiefe founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:124195:24"/>of faith. Secondly, becauſe, though men may be ſuppoſed to agree, in principles, and fundamentals; yet notwithſtanding, may diſſent in thoſe things, that are deduced, and concluded out of thoſe Principles; therefore, he deſires them to be joyned alſo together in the ſame judgement; which may direct them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one, and the ſame practiſe. Thirdly, though men may be conceived to agree, in the ſame mind, and in the ſame judgement; yet, becauſe ſome are, often, ſo in love with their own formes of ſpeaking, and ſo fond of their owne invented expreſſions, that rather, than they will bee divorced from that new phraſe, to which they have wedded themſelves, they will chooſe to ſeparate, and be divided from the ſociety of the faithfull brethren; as the caſe ſtood with<note n="f" place="margin">Secrat. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>32.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorius</hi> the Heretique, who, in the beginning, did not erre, touching the Unity of Chriſts perſon, in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of the natures of God, and man: but only diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked, that <hi>Mary</hi> ſhould be called the Mother of God; which form of ſpeaking, when ſome demonſtrated to be very fitting, and unavoydable, if Chriſt were God and Man in the vnity of the ſame perſon; he choſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to deny the Unity of Chriſts perſon, than to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge his temerity, and raſhnes, in reproving that forme of ſpeech, which<note n="g" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Feild, l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>in fine,</hi> of the Church.</note> the vſe of the Church had anciently received, and allowed; For this confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, it was, that the Apoſtle exhorteth alſo, that they all [ſpeake] the ſame thing; which in other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, is to hold faſt<note n="h" place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.13.</note> the forme of ſound words; and called ſound, or wholſome ſpeech, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.8. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, and laſtly, becauſe, though all this be agreed on; yet if there be reſpect of<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jam.</hi> 2.1.</note> [perſons] in receiving, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining the goſpell; one man pinning his faith upon the ſleeve of <hi>Paul;</hi> another raviſhed with the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 18.24.</note> elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of <hi>Apollo;</hi> a third crying up <hi>Cophas</hi> above them all; ſo that the doctrine is not entertained, after<note n="k" place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.13.</note> a <hi>Theſſalonian</hi> integrity, as the word of [God],
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:124195:24"/>(whoſe<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.16.</note> power alone it is unto ſalvation, in them that beleeve) but as the word of [man]; becauſe, from this conſideration, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> obſerved [con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions] to ariſe among them, as we read, <hi>ver.</hi> 11.12. therfore, he perſwades them, by the name of the Lord Ieſus Chriſt, unto Unity, and unto Unanimity: for <hi>ver.</hi> 3. is Chriſt [divided?] that is, by a reſolution of the interrogative into an affirmative, Chriſt himſelfe is not divided: and therefore they that would be coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Chriſtians indeed, and truly in him, muſt not nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be divided; either, from the whole body of the Church Catholique, at large, or elſe from love, and V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity among themſelves: For, if they be [divided], or doe but cauſe, or foment [diviſions], in the Church; the ſame Apoſtle is peremptory, elſewhere, <hi>Rom.</hi> 19.18. that they that are ſuch, ſerve not our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>To end all: Thus then let all the loyall ſonnes of Peace doe; As, labour to ſpeake, and to teach one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly [truth]; ſo alſo to doe the ſame in<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.15.</note> [love]; and let me, (in this needfull time,) be bold to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort you all, in the words of the Schiſme-hating Apoſtle, to his <hi>Phillippians, cap.</hi> 2.1.2.3. If there be, therefore, any conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of love, if any fellowſhip of the ſpirit, if any bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of mercies; fullfill ye my joy, that ye be like-minded, having the ſame love, being of one accord, of one mind, let nothing be done through ſtrife, or vain-glory: Thus let us do; and it ſhall be well with us, at the laſt; and know though the ſinner, and lover of diſcords, ſin<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccles.</hi> 8.12.</note> an hundred times, yet God ſhall, one day, pay him home, in his own coine; For, when the Peace-lover, and the Peace-maker ſhall be ſurely bleſſed; God ſhall deale with them, as <hi>Iacob,</hi> on his death-bed,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.9.</note> doomed <hi>Simeon,</hi> and <hi>Levi,</hi> (thoſe Brethren in iniquity) <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.7. Even divide them in <hi>Jacob,</hi> and ſcatter them in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and thoſe, that ſtudy ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and ſcandalous [Separations:] Loe! When
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:124195:25"/>all the Nations of the World ſhall bee gathered before him; (to make their ſhame more publique, and yet their confuſion moſt juſt;) the juſt Lord, and the<note n="o" place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8.</note> righteous Iudge of the whole earth, ſhall, (out of the juſt, and equall Law of Retaliation) hee ſhall [ſeparate] the peaceable from them, as a ſhepheard [divideth] the ſheepe from the goates, <hi>Matth,</hi> 25 32.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Motive. </seg>
               </label> If any Church, in the whole World, were ever en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to obedience, this way; ours ought to be, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all: In all the booke of God, wee read of no one Nation [<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 1, 8.14.</note> ſo neare] unto the Lord, in his ſpeciall grace, and favour, as was the <hi>Iewiſh;</hi> Loe! ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt, Pſalm</hi> 135.4. <hi>The Lord hath choſen Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob unto himſelfe, and Iſrael for his peculiar Treaſure;</hi> The <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, was as that<note n="q" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.6.</note> Figtree in the Vineyard, that is, not, as<note n="r" place="margin">Ribera in Joch, <hi>1.7.12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ribera</hi> interprets it, ſome eminent Prince, or Magiſtrate, in the Church; but the particular Church of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> planted by the ſpeciall hand of God, in the Vineyard, or the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſall Church, at large; hedged in, and fenced with his owne protection; the leaſt annoyance, or injury offered it, was as tender to him; as the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his owne eye, <hi>Zech.</hi> 2.8. And yet, though God is ſaid to have knowne them onely, of all the families of the earth; hee meanes, with the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſpeciall favour, and approbation, <hi>Amos</hi> 3.2. Nevertheleſſe, when even this choyce, and ſelected people, afterwards degenerated into Civill rents firſt, and then into ſuch as divided them from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and, moſt of all, from God, by ſuperſtition, and idolatry: theſe ſinnes of theirs made a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration betweene them, and their God, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 52.2.</p>
            <p>Now, my beloved, wee cannot bee more deare to the Lord, than was this ancient Church of his, unto him: will they have miracles? Loe! ſee them,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:124195:25"/>as <hi>Leah</hi> ſaid of <hi>Gad, Gen.</hi> 30.11. comming in a troupe; The Sea ſhall roule into an heape, and the paths thereof bee dried up before them; <hi>Exod.</hi> 14. <hi>Iordan</hi> alſo ſhall bee driven back, and fly, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 114.5. Is not this enough? then ſhall the Sunne ſtand ſtill, in <hi>Gibeon,</hi> and the Moone, in the valley of <hi>Ajalon, Ioſh.</hi> 10.13. Will not this doe? then ſhall the very Rockes, before them, bee diſſolved into Rivers; yea, the Heavens raine-downe the food of Angels upon them, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 78.5. Loe! their King cloathed them in skarlet, and put on ornaments of gold upon their apparrell, with other delights, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.24 Their little hill <hi>Hermon,</hi> and their moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of <hi>Zion</hi> were wet with the Dew of Gods bounty; <hi>Pſalm</hi> 133.3. In ſhort, thouſands, and tenne thouſands ſhall fly before them, if they have ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: each page of their ſtory is but the record of their miracles, and of their peculiarized favours.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mutato nomine de to:</hi> change but the name, and wee are the men; for, wherein out-ſtript they us? They were delivered from the heavy bondage of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> ſo that, though they had layen among the pots, yet became they as the wings of a Dove, whoſe wings were covered with ſilver, and whoſe feathers were like gold, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 68.13. and, have not wee beene reskued from a worſe thraldome? delivered from the vaſſaladge, and bondage of Popiſh ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; farre more dangerous, than the blackeſt, or the moſt <hi>Cimmerian</hi> darkeneſſe: and woe, woe bee unto us, if wee long to returne back, to that rotten garlick againe, and to that heavy yoke of bondage! They had <hi>Manna</hi> from Heaven; ſo have wee the full meaſures (farre ſurpaſſing their <hi>Omers,</hi> or their <hi>Ephah's</hi>) of the ſpirituall, and the beſt <hi>Manna</hi> in the Goſpell: They had Sea-deliverances; remember the never to bee forgotten yeare of eighty eight, had not wee? They were as firebrands pluckt out of the burning,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:124195:26"/>
               <hi>Amos,</hi> 4.11. Say, fift of <hi>November;</hi> were not wee? The Starres from Heaven fought for them, in their courſes, as in the dayes of <hi>Siſera, Iudg.</hi> 5.20. and the elements conſpired their victories; How often as great experiments have wee taſted? ſo that, we may well here reſume that Diſtich, in the<note n="*" place="margin">Claudian, in laude Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſti.</note> Poet, of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<q>
                  <l>O nimiûmdilecta Deo, cuimilitat aether,</l>
                  <l>Et conjurati veniunt ad claſſica venti.</l>
               </q> But now, woe is mee! ſhall I goe on? ſee then; they ſcorned their <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> and, as bloudy <hi>Atreus,</hi> in the<note n="r" place="margin">Seneca Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaed. in Thyeſte.</note> 
               <hi>Tragaedy,</hi> they cry out, <hi>Ruat in me, modò in fratrem;</hi> to ruine him, they curſed themſelves; His<note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.25.</note> bloud, ſay they, bee upon us, and upon our Children! and to this Day, ſome ſay, the bloudy iſſue runs on their wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, about the paſſion: O heavy curſe! O direfull im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precation! how hath their Lambe beene turned, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſince, into a Lion to them? O barren figtree, long ſince, haſt thou had thy <hi>ſuccîde;</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 13.7.</note> cut it downe, ſaith God, why cumbreth it the ground? O how are thy branches become ſcattered, in the day of the Lords wrath upon thee, yea, even as very dung upon the face of the earth? <hi>Ier.</hi> 18.17.</p>
            <p>O <hi>England, England,</hi> what is thy ſilver alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come<note n="u" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.22.</note> droſſe? thy Bethel, a Bethaven? O where is all the fruit of Gods long bounty, and favours to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thee? have they bred onely<note n="x" place="margin">Jud. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> wantonnes, and not obedience in thee? Loe! I am loath to bee the Meſſenger of ſo evill tidings unto thee, and to tell thee ſo bitter a word; yet muſt I not ſew pillowes under thine arme-holes, or dawbe thee with<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13.10.18.</note> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered mortar, to flatter thy ſecurity; Nor have I this bitter word for thee, from the whiſper of a <hi>Mahomet's</hi> dove; nor is it the dreame of an <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſticall</hi> braine; No, I have it from the mouth
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:124195:26"/>of the Lord God himſelfe, who bids mee tell thee, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did old <hi>Iſrael, Deut,</hi> 28.59. <hi>The Lord will make thy plagues wonderfull, even great plagues, and of long continuance, and ſore ſickneſſes, and of long continuance, and they ſhall cleave unto thee: and, take heed, thou doe not be-come, as they, a</hi> Loammi, <hi>and a</hi> Loruamah, Hoſ. 1.6.9. <hi>A not-my people, and not having obtained mercy:</hi> Behold! the owner of the Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree is now in viſitation; hee hath often, and long, ſent his Meſſengers, as <hi>Ioſhua</hi> did his<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſh.</hi> 2 1.</note> ſpies, before him, to ſee how his Figtree thrives, after ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares dreſſing; His Vine-dreſſers, the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpell, have beene long planting with their Doctrine, pulling away the ſtones of oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, tearing up the weeds of prophanneſſe, roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up the furſes of Hereſie, and the thornes of Schiſme, and faction; they have beene<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.5.</note> hedging with Diſcipline; paring, and pruning with their ſeaſonable reproofes: In ſhort, what could the Lord have done more for this Church of ours, than what hee hath done for it? Loe now! becauſe his<note n="b" place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 36.16. and, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23.37.</note> Meſſengers have beene ſleighted, and ſo lightly ſet by of us; Hee now ſeemes himſelfe to come riding in viſitation; and ſurely, when the Lord comes himſelfe, eſpecially in a circuite of vengeance, or judgement; as ſoone may the ſtubble hope to ſtand before a<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.29.</note> conſuming fire; as a ſecure, and an impenitent people beare up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the fierce wrath of ſo dreadfull, and incenſed a Iudge: It is a remarkeable paſſage, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.10. When the Law was given, upon mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> with thunderings, and lightenings, and the noiſe of the Trumpet, and ſmoake, and ſuch like ghaſtly repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentations, ſetting out the mightineſſe, and the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midable power of that great God, who gave the Law; and conſidering, how fearefull that Law muſt needs be to the breakers of it; which was ſo<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.21.</note> terrible in the firſt giving; They ſaid unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſpeake [thou]
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:124195:27"/>
               <hi>with us, and wee will heare; but let not</hi> [GOD] <hi>ſpeake with us, leaſt wee die:</hi> as if they had ſaid, Let <hi>Moſes,</hi> a man of our owne mould, ſpeake to us; or, in Saint <hi>Paul's</hi> expreſſion, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.19. Let the Law bee or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, in the hand of a [Mediatour;] Let there bee ſome to intercede, and to ſtand in the<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.30.</note> gappe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the Lords power, and our impotence; for otherwiſe, if wee ſhall fall [immediately] into the hands of the Lord himſelfe; (who, in his wrath, is a conſuming fire) wee ſhall all bee waſted into aſhes, and bee utterly, and hopeleſly conſumed: Hence is that of the Apoſtle, It's a<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.31.</note> fearefull thing to fall into the hands of the living God.</p>
            <p>For this cauſe likewiſe, yee ſhall notice it, throughout the Prophets; that, when they have found themſelves to become a reproach, and the word of the Lord, a deriſion dayly; ſo that they had no hopes left them to prevaile for a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation: they would then recommend the cauſe into the Lords owne hand, and deſire him to behold the obſtinate perverſeneſſe of a Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious people; which done, there ſtill enſued a ſpeedy, and a dreadfull overthrow; ſee <hi>Ieremiah,</hi> 20.8. and <hi>Lam.</hi> 3.14. compared with, <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.3.9.</p>
            <p>But here, mee thinkes, I heare ſome Engliſh <hi>Gallio,</hi> as hee, in the <hi>Acts,</hi> 18.14.17. interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Saint <hi>Paul;</hi> (One, I meane, that careth for none of theſe things,) ſtepping in, with, a Why doeſt thou thus diſcredit thy Nation? are wee not fenced? are wee not friended? are wee not populous? Is not the Temple? Is not the Goſpell, among us?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label>
               <hi>Ah ſinfull Nation! ah people laden with iniquity!</hi> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.4. of <hi>Iſrael: O Hieruſalem, Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem how long ſhall theſe thy vaine thoughts of immunity,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:124195:27"/>from ruine, lodge within thee; whileſt yet thine heart is not waſhed from its wickedneſſe?</hi> Jer. 4.14. I could bid thee, as the Prophet Jer. 7.12. go to Shiloh, a place, where the Lord, once, let his name, yet, now, it is become, (for the ſecurity of them that dwelt therein) a very denne of dragons; and again, <hi>Jer.</hi> 49.3. Howl, oh Heſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bon, for Ai is ſpoyled: and, others ruine ſhould be our warning; their <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, our <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, their ſuffering, our leſſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings: look about you, and ſee what a ſhambles is all Chriſtendome become, What<note n="*" place="margin">Matt. 27.33.</note> Golgatha's, and what<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 1.19.</note> Acheldema's, or fields of blood are hare, and, how ſeem our neighbours Churches, long, to have been whirried about in a continuall tumult, whileſt we, as the Centre, ſtand ſtill, and immoveable?
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>;</l>
               </q> ſaith 8. <hi>Gregory</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">S. Greg. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zian. in Od. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nazianzene;</hi> Do the towns totter, and can the neighbouring cottage be unſhaken? do the mighty Cedars ſuffer a ſhock, and can the humble Pine-tree be ſecure? and populous and warlike Nations depopulated, and waſted? and can we look on, and be ſecure? But, wo is me! when Iſrael had a divorce, yet her treacherous ſiſter <hi>Judah</hi> would not fear, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.8. O fooliſh people, and unwiſe; do we thus tempt, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke the Lord unto anger? nay, do we not, rather, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke our ſelves, to the confuſion of our own faces? as the Prophet ſpeaks, <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.10. <hi>confer Pro.</hi> 8.36. Be not deceived, God is not<note n="g" place="margin">Gal. 6.7.</note> mocked.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, to hover no longer; Look what <hi>Idus</hi> in Judg. 3.20. ſaid unto <hi>Eglon,</hi> then King of Moab, in another kind; I have a meſſage from God unto thee, oh King; ſo have I unto thee, oh England; and it is, in the Prophet <hi>Nahums</hi> words, unto vaunting Nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veh, <hi>Nah.</hi> 3.8. Art thou better then populous No? (he means<note n="h" place="margin">Junius ad Nah. <hi>3.8.</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer ler. <hi>46.25.</hi>
               </note> Alexandria in Egypt) that was ſcituate among the rivers, that had the waters round about it, whoſe rampart was the ſea, (right Englands Embleme) and her wall was from the ſea; Ethiopia, and Egypt were her ſtrength, <hi>Put</hi> and <hi>Lubin</hi> were her helpers; yet was
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:124195:28"/>ſhe carried away: She, ſo populous, ſo fenced, ſo friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: and what was the cauſe? ſee it, <hi>ver.</hi> 5. Behold, I am againſt thee, ſaith the Lord of hoſts: lo! what a word is here? I am againſt thee, ſaith the Lord; in<note n="i" place="margin">Quod reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium quaeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ubi [au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor] remedti non concilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur? Hegeſip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus, de excid. urb. Hieruſal. p. <hi>672.</hi> in Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cephal. in octa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vo. <hi>See Ier. 3.</hi>
               </note> vain, then, is ſalvation hoped fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the mountains, if the Lord, who is the God of the mountains, be againſt us Oh wo, wo, wo be unto us, if the Lord of Hoſts be againſt us: if the Rock of our ſalvation, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtyles him, hath forſaken us: If God be [for] us, who can be [againſt] us? ſaith the great Apoſtle; but, if God be once [a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt] us, who can be [for] us? <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.31.</p>
            <p>In a word, let me tell you; and let my words, not as mine, but as the Lords, ſink deeply into your medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: the word is this; That ſin, that black, and ougly monſter ſin, is of more force to weaken a ſtate, and to ruine a Kingdom; than all the ſtrength of an Army can be, be it as potent, and numerous; as that of <hi>Zorah,</hi> the Aethiopian, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 14.9. one of the greateſt, that we read of, in the Scriptures, even an hoſte of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand thouſand.</p>
            <p>But, O my ſoul, why haſt thou made me to dwell, thus long, in theſe<note n="k" place="margin">Cant. 1.5. &amp; Pſal. 120.5.</note> black tents of Kedar? and, why do I, with <hi>Noah's</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 8.7.</note> Raven, fly croaking, thus, about the dead carkaſſes of ſinfull men; floating perhaps, yet drowned in ſin, and ſhame? Surely, my beloved Chriſtians, theſe are not times for us, (tis in vain to flatter) to begin, or end our Sermons, with thoſe of <hi>Ezekiel's</hi> viſions, that promiſe peace, and deliverance; but, as the Prophets, <hi>Nahum, Habakkick,</hi> and <hi>Malachi,</hi> do their prophecies, with the burthen of the Lord, the burthen of the Lord, that is, ſome<note n="m" place="margin">Junius, ad <hi>2</hi> King. <hi>9.25.</hi>
               </note> commination, and threat of a judgement, heavie as thoſe burthens, under which <hi>Iſſachar</hi> ſtooped down, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.14.</p>
            <p>But ſtay, what, art thou all for judgement? ſurely, that is the portion of impenitent, remorſeleſſe, and unrelenting ſinners, there is no<note n="n" place="margin">Iſa. 57.21.</note> peace, ſaith my God, unto the wicked: But yet, my breaſt ſhall not a wayes be, as ſome thunder-cloud, whoſe vapours ne're leave working, till they vent themſelves with terrours to the world; my ſpeech ſhall rather ſtrive to be as King
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:124195:28"/>
               <hi>Davids</hi> plentifull rain, to<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 68.9.</note> refreſh the inheritance of the Lord: For what? is there no<note n="p" place="margin">Ier. 8.22.</note> balme yet left in Gilead? no mean, to intercede, as<note n="q" place="margin">Gen. 37.21.</note> 
               <hi>Reuben,</hi> to ſtay the ſlaughter of an endangered <hi>Ioſeph?</hi> no <hi>Moſes,</hi> in the<note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 106.23.</note> gap? ſurely yes; ſee your remedie, in <hi>Amos.</hi> 4.12. <hi>Prepare to meet thy God, O Iſrael:</hi> O Iſrael, Iſrael, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance is ſo welcome a Courtier, to ſollicite at the throne of heaven, that it ever ſpeeds in its ſuits: [meet] then thy God in righteouſneſſe, (even now, whileſt the day of grace, and<note n="s" place="margin">2 Cor. 6.1.</note> ſalvation laſteth) and we may reſt aſſured, as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaks, Chap. 64.5. that the Lord will be readie, to [meet] us in mercie: get we into this Arke, before the flood come; gather we our Manna, and prepare to our eternall Sabbath, in the Even, before hand; <hi>Qui laborat in veſpere, Sabbati, veſcetur in Sabbato,</hi> ſay the Rabbins: be we fore-warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſo fore-armed too;<note n="t" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bp.</hi> An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drews, in Praefat. ad concion. in Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodo Provin. p. <hi>26.</hi> inter opera poſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huma.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>praeſtantior,</hi> ſaid an eminent Prelate.</p>
            <p>So then, let every one mend one; and (declining that humour of declaiming on the diſmembred con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the times,) let every one of us, in particular, think, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of himſelf, in the act of a ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condemning conſcience, that of all ſinners, I am the [chiefeſt], 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 1.15. and, that, for [my ſake], as good <hi>Ionah</hi> acknowledged, <hi>Ion.</hi> 1.12. the tempeſt of the Lords wrath is abroad, in Schiſmes, and diviſions, and in other grievous, heart-wounding diſtempers; and let every one of us, in this regard, as the King of Nineveh adviſed, in a time of danger, and diſtreſſe, <hi>Iona.</hi> 3.8. cry [mightily] unto the Lord: ſurely, if we could faſten, in every of our particular ſouls, this one meditation, that, I am the [chiefeſt] of ſinners, and that for [my] ſake is the Lord diſpleaſed, ſo highly; we could not, but exchange our mutuall invectives, into moſt zealous, and importunate clamours, at the gate of heaven, for pardon; and, not beſeech alone, but, as it were, by an army of joynt devotions, even beſiege the throne of that Majeſtie, who will not<note n="v" place="margin">Lam. 3 8.</note> ſhut out the prayers of his poore,<note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 102.17</note> deſtitute, Church, and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:124195:29"/>children; and let us never leave wreſtling with the Lord, till, with good <hi>Iacob,</hi> we impetrate, and<note n="y" place="margin">Gen. 32.26.</note> obtain the bleſſing: I remember<note n="z" place="margin">Zanchius, l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi> de Naturâ Dei.</note> 
               <hi>Zanchy</hi> hath reſembled this, that I am now cloſing up my Sermon with, unto a company of ſhip-men; in a ſhip, tied by a cable-rope, unto a Rock: Theſe ſhip men are poore, penitent ſuppliants, within the ſhip of the Church, riding, and toſſed in a ſea of miſerie; this rope is prayer; and the<note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.4.</note> Rock, is Chriſt: Now, when they draw at the Cable, they ſeem to pull the Rock to the ſhip, and not the ſhip to the Rock; and yet, in truth, the eaſe is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe; the Rock ſtands fixed, and immoveable, and, in the iſſue, it is the ſhip, that is drawn home to the Rock, not the Rock, to the ſhip: ſo, the more we draw at the Cable, and are importunate with God, in prayer; the nigher ſtil do we approach, unto the<note n="b" place="margin">Deut. 32.15.</note> Rock of our ſalvation, Chriſt Jeſus; and the more we are ſtill drawn out of the waters of affliction, and tribula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: my deare brethren, we cannot enough beleeve, how melodious, and raviſhing in the cares of the Lord our joynt-devotions, and ſervent prayers will be: what<note n="c" place="margin">Eccleſ. 9.10.</note> 
               <hi>Solomon,</hi> therefore, adviſeth, at large, let us be advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to do, in this particular, even do it with all our [might]; and doubt not of a gracious<note n="d" place="margin">Matth. 7.7, 8.</note> ſucceſſe.</p>
            <p>And, as we would pray for peace, and ſalvation to our own ſouls; ſo let us be importunate with others al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, to follow after the things, that make for peace: and, if it ſo fall out, that, when thou art perſwading for peace, they are ſtil making ready for<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 120.7.</note> warre; and, all thy endeavours, this way, are but like unto the ſtone Diacletes; which, though it have very many excellent ſoveraignties in it, yet it loſeth them all, if it be put in a [dead] mans mouth; ſo thy godly perſwaſion unto unity, and peace, (which is the onely pearl, and jewell of a Chriſtian) though it may have a ſoveraigne ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue in it, among the ſons of quietneſſe, and peace; yet it loſeth all, if it be put into an eare, or an heart, that is dead in ſin; or, if it be applied to a man, who affects rather, to be ſome body, in the trouble, than no body,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:124195:29"/>in the peace of the Church: notwithſtanding, do thou thy endeavour; and reſt aſſured, though the iſſue from them fail of thy zealous expectation; yet, what King <hi>David</hi> ſaid of the prayers, that he made of his enemies, ſhall hold true of thy endeavours; The comfort, and reward of them ſhall<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 35.13.</note> return into thine own boſome: Neither indeed, can the raigning, and continuance of Schiſmes, and Diviſions, in the Church, (chiefly, in this dotage of the world) much ſtagger, or afflict thee; for, what <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid of the fiery triall, holds true here, This is no<note n="g" place="margin">1 Pet, 4.12.</note> [ſtrange] thing, that hath hapned among us: lo! it hath ever been ſo, (throughout all ages of the Church) ſince the original, and firſt<note n="h" place="margin">Gen. 3.15.</note> breach made betwixt the two ſeeds, in Paradiſe: yea, the probabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the thing it ſelf, is grounded, ſaith our Apoſtle here, on the [neceſſity] of a [greater] evil, that [muſt] be, in the Church; and that is hereſie; ſchiſmes, and diviſions [may] be, for, hereſies [muſt] be; for, ſo is the Text, <hi>For, firſt of all, when ye come together in the Church, I hear that there are diviſions among you, and I partly beleeve it; for there [muſt] be alſo hereſies among you, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I conclude all, with that zealous exhortation of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paul</hi> unto his Corinthians, among whom he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected variety of Schiſmes, and Diviſions; and unto whom he had ſhewed the danger, and ill conſequence of them; and, willing to raiſe up their hearts unto a deſire of the remedie thereof, which was the contrary amitie, and unity, ſaith; Finally, brethred, farewell: be perfect, be of good comfort, be of one minde, live in<note n="i" place="margin">2 Cor. 13.11.</note> peace, and the God of love, and peace ſhall be with you: This God grant unto us, and unto his holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique Church, for his dear Son ſake, Jeſus Chriſt the righteous; To whom with the Father, and the bleſſed Spirit be all honour, praiſe, and glory, from hence forth, and for ever.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <closer>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
